<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Iacobs troublesome iourney to Bethel conteining a briefe exposition, or excellent treatise of the four first verses of the 33. chapter of Genesis: Set foorth by Iohn Overton, Maister of Arts.</title>
            <title>Jacobs troublesome journey to Bethel.</title>
            <author>Overton, John, Master of Arts.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1586</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 123 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 46 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A08614</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 18924</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S104948</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99840678</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99840678</idno>
            <idno type="VID">177190</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A08614)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 177190)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 897:04)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Iacobs troublesome iourney to Bethel conteining a briefe exposition, or excellent treatise of the four first verses of the 33. chapter of Genesis: Set foorth by Iohn Overton, Maister of Arts.</title>
                  <title>Jacobs troublesome journey to Bethel.</title>
                  <author>Overton, John, Master of Arts.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 75, [5] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Ioseph Barnes,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At Oxford :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Anno D. 1586.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Appended, with caption title: A prayer against the enemies of the Church of Christ, vnder the borrowed name or speach of Iacob.</note>
                  <note>Pages 35-36 torn, with some loss of print.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Jacob --  (Biblical patriarch) --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Genesis --  Commentaries --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:177190:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:177190:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>IACOBS TROVBLE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SOME IOVR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NEY TO BE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>THEL:</p>
            <p>Conteining a briefe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition, or excellent Treatiſe of the four firſt verſes of the 33. Chapter of GENESIS: <hi>Set foorth by</hi> IOHN OVER<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TON, <hi>Maiſter of Arts.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>GENESIS 31. 3.</bibl>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reuertere ad terram Patrum tuorum: &amp; ad cognationem tuam, &amp; ero tecum.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>AT OXFORD, <hi>Printed by</hi> IOSEPH BARNES, <hi>Anno D.</hi> 1586.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:177190:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:177190:2"/>
            <head>TO HIS MOST COVRTEOVS, AND LOVING FRIEND, MA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter WILLIAM BRENT: IOHN OVERTON <hi>wiſheth</hi> grace, peace, &amp; all true fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <hi>licitie in Ieſus Chriſtour</hi> Sauiour.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>ORLDLY riches haue I none where with to ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the ſhew of a grate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full hart, but of ſuch me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niall ſtuffe as God hath lent me, I preſent &amp; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicate vnto your good name, &amp; friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly acceptation this litle booke (as the firſt fruits of my ſtudy) intituled, Iacobs troubleſome iourney to Bethel. His brother Eſau came againſt him with foure hundred men. Whereby is ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied by theſe two brethren, the miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble troubles betweene the malignant Synagogue of Sathan, and the militant Church of Chriſt: as alſo other matter very neceſſary to be conſidered in this piece of Scripture. And though it bee litle in quantitie, and in habite ſutelike according to the hability of the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor:
<pb facs="tcp:177190:3"/>
yet when I gladly cal to minde, &amp; with no ſmall comfort remember your vnfeigned friendſhippes, and fauours towardes mee heretofore at Ilming<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton, I cannot but be aſhamed of my ſelfe, that abilitie doeth not afforde my hande ſo much to write, as my heart willeth my tongue to vtter howe deepely indebted I am to your great curteſie. But conſidering that your due and full rewarde is laide vp vntill ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther day, in an other place, by another man, of al fulneſſe, &amp; habilitie, Chriſt Ieſus the high Steward, and paie-ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of all, I am to requeſt you til that time come, which I truſt ſhall not be long, to accept my good heart, which in all poſſible dutie is and ſhall bee yours bounden to command. A ſmale rewarde for ſuch benefites, I confeſſe, yet as kinde, and dutifull a mite, as the greateſt valure of a farther ſumme. And ſith that the moſt precious iewel in this worlde, which man can ſhew, or giue to man, is vnfeigned loue, then truely the loue that creepeth when it cannot goe, is aſwell to be accompted of, and eſteemed, as loue,
<pb facs="tcp:177190:3"/>
nay perhappes the rather than when it carieth a higher looke, and a loftier countenance: for to ſay the trueth, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefites which are liberall for the gyft, &amp; grateful for the repay, are in that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect ſaid to bee great, or litle, as the affection of the heart is great or litle. But weying my vnhability, I am forced to ſay with Virgil: <hi>Grates perſoluere dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nas non opis eſt noſtroe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This conſideration therefore, as al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo your zeale in religion, and loue of learning, did altogither moue mee to pen this worke.</p>
            <p>And in this treatiſe is this eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie to be obſerued, how Iacob, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by is ſignified the Church of Chriſt, hath beene maliced, &amp; griuouſlie bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dened by Eſau, the malignant Church, from the beginning. All places are ſo fraught and full of examples here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, that wee neede not experimentes from farre. Only the Church of Rome in this place ſhall ſerue vs in ſteede of manie: which as long as ſhee was vnder perſecuting TYRANTS, and ſharpened as it were vppon a grynd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing whetſtone, ſhee was found, and
<pb facs="tcp:177190:4"/>
truely called the only nurſe, or mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſe of all godlineſſe, and continen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy: in whom all the giftes of Chriſtian religion, and honeſt life did moſt abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly excel, &amp; moſt brightly ſhine. But afterwards (the caſe being quite altred) ſhe began to malice Iacob, and to laie grieuous burdens vpon his ſhoulders, chiefly, when in ſteed of danger, perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution &amp; vexatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s; Riches, pride, ſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuouſnes, &amp; alielenes their companion came in place, &amp; crept into the Church. And when as Byſhops in ſteed of mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs began to be perſecutors of Martyrs themſelues: and the ſtrength, and force of the goſpel decaied, &amp; weakned more &amp; more, into what wickednes &amp; abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination that church did run, &amp; fall, let euery one conſider, &amp; iudge with him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe: I am not able ſufficiently to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe it according to the indignity, &amp; hainouſneſſe thereof.</p>
            <p>This example, and note (by the way) ſhalbe ſufficient for my purpoſe, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>allie, for that the matter appeareth ſo plaine, and manifeſt in al the bookes of the godly.</p>
            <p>And thus ſubmitting my ſelfe &amp; this
<pb facs="tcp:177190:4"/>
ſmal treatiſe vnto your frindly protecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, &amp; wonted fauor, referring the faults rather to the ſimplenes of my skil, then to my willing mind, and wiſhing you as great pleaſure, &amp; liking in the reading, as it hath bin ſome paine, and trauell to me in penning: I commend you to the direction and guiding of God his holie ſpirite, who grant you proſperous ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe in all godlines. From my ſtudie at Welsborne, the firſt day of April, 1586.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Yours with all dutifull endeuors, euer at commandement: IOHN OVERTON.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="Scripture">
            <pb facs="tcp:177190:5"/>
            <head>GENESIS XXXiij.</head>
            <p n="1">1 And as IACOB lift vp his eies, &amp; looked, beholde E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SAV came, and with him four hundred men, and he diuided the childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to LEAH &amp; RA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>HEL, &amp; to the two maides.</p>
            <p n="2">2 And hee put the maides and their children foremoſt, and LEAH and hir children after, and RAHEL and IO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SEPH hindermoſt.</p>
            <p n="3">3 So he went before them, and bowed himſelfe to the ground ſeuen times, vntill he came neare his brother.</p>
            <p n="4">4 Then ESAV ranne to meet him, and fel on his neck, and embraced him and kiſſed him, and they wept.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="exegesis">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:177190:5"/>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T hath bin euer a thing common in the world, and not ſo commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as noiſome, to all e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates, that pride, enuy, &amp; couetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, <note place="margin">Enuy, coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſſe, and pride, ſoweth diſcord in the worlde.</note> ſhould ſowe diſcord among the ſons of men, to ſtir vp not only princes againſt princes, but alſo one brother againſt another. Wherof al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though <note place="margin">1. Reg. 1. 5.</note> there be many exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ples exta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient to inſtruct the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that haue any doci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, yet there is none of more importa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce than this of <hi>Iacob,</hi> &amp; <hi>Eſau,</hi> ſet downe by <hi>Moiſes.</hi> for in it who liſt may beholde (as in a glaſſe) the moſt lamentable gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boils between the malignant ſynagogue of lathan, &amp; the militant church of chriſt.</p>
            <p>The two principal cauſes of the hatred <note place="margin">The cauſes of the hatred of Eſau againſt Iacob.</note> of <hi>Eſau</hi> againſt <hi>Iacob,</hi> is not vnknowen to them which haue indifferently bin con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſant in the ſcriptures, namely the loſſe of his birth-right and blesſing, wherein <note place="margin">Gen. 25. Heb. 12.</note> none was to blame but himſelfe, which contemned the one, and by preuoking his mother, through his ſtrange wiues, was foreſtalled of the other.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:177190:6"/>
In this portion of ſcripture the mee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting <note place="margin">Gen. 26. In what array Iacob put his family.</note> of theſe two brethren is preſcribed, &amp; in what arraie poore fearefull <hi>Iacob,</hi> put his company to entertaine that ſauage knight his brother <hi>Eſau,</hi> honorably vſing this courteous &amp; humble demeanor as an ordinary meane offered of the Lord, for the appeaſing of his brothers wrath.</p>
            <p>Although there be no great felicity in <note place="margin">The holy ghoſt is not tied to a me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod.</note> diviſions where the holy ghoſt is not tied to a Methode, yet becauſe this piece of Scripture is in a manner diuided to our hands, let vs by Gods help in this our ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſtand vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> theſe four points only.</p>
            <p>In the firſt place the injuries &amp; miſeries of <hi>Iacob,</hi> &amp; ſo of Chriſts Church at theſe <note place="margin">Gal. 1. 16.</note> daies, whereof <hi>Iacob</hi> was then a figure, &amp; the pomp &amp; power of <hi>Eſau:</hi> &amp; ſo of the ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagogue of <hi>Sathan,</hi> which in our time, <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſau</hi> did then repreſent, &amp; to be noted out of theſe words: <hi>And Iacob lift vp his eies and loked, behold Eſau came, and with him foure hundred men.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly the diſpoſing of <hi>Iacobs</hi> fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily, is to be obſerued, becauſe of his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion, <note place="margin">The diſpoſing of Iacobs peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple.</note> in theſe next wordes: <hi>And hee diuided the children to Leah &amp; Rahel and the two maides, &amp; he put the maids
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:177190:6"/>
&amp; their children foremoſt, and Leah &amp; hir children after, &amp; Rahel &amp; Ioſeph hindermoſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly we haue to conſider the cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage, deuotion, and humility of <hi>Iacob,</hi> in <note place="margin">The deuotio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, courage, and humilitie of Iacob.</note> this meeting, in this third verſe: <hi>So hee went before them, and bowed himſelfe ſeuen times, vntill he came neare to his brother.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly is ſet forth the unlooked-for louing meeting of <hi>Eſau</hi> &amp; the ioy of them <note place="margin">The louing entertainme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of Eſau.</note> both in this fourth verſe. <hi>Then Eſau ran to meete him, &amp; embraced him, and fel on his necke and kiſſed him, and they wept.</hi>
            </p>
            <div n="1" type="part">
               <head>The firſt part.</head>
               <p>COncerning the firſt, we haue to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider <note place="margin">The feare of Iacob. Gen. 32.</note> of theſe wordes, <hi>Iacob lift vp his eies and looked,</hi> the miſerable plight that <hi>Iacob</hi> was in, which looked euer among when <hi>Eſau</hi> ſhould lay blouddie handes vpon him, and that the feare of his power, which was a litle before re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported to him by the meſſengers, had ſmitten him to the heart, before hee ſawe them, which made him (no doubt) with terror to looke vp ſo often, ſo as he
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:177190:7"/>
might ſee, when he came, whom hee moſt neceſſarilie met, for it was in the waie to <hi>Bethel,</hi> whither God had commaunded him to returne: neither had hee forgot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ge.</hi> 31.</note> his Mothers advertiſement when ſhe ſent him from home, that his Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Eſau</hi> was comforted againſt him, meaning to kill him: which cauſed him greatelie to feare the inuincible tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie <note place="margin">The tyrannie of Death.</note> of death, which he thought to bee at hand. For here, by the way, we maie note, howe Death is daylie ranging, &amp; raging in the worlde ſundry wales: the power and force whereof which of the Patriarks or Monarches of the world was once able to withſtand: no not the dreadfull Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie of Kinges or Keaſars could not at anie time haue her at becke or check, no craftie conueiance or drifte in Lawe, could circumuent hir, no worldlie wealth could bribe hir, nor no Phariſaical holy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, Religion of Biſhops, Monkiſh au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteritie or prayers of Prieſtes coulde euer intreate hir. No citizens poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie or handie craftes labour coulde ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh hir of houſe or Towne. Finallie no ſtrength of nature, no reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of man could at any time reſiſt or giue hir the foile.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:177190:7"/>
This force, and great feare of death being ſtroken into <hi>Iacob,</hi> knowing the malice of his barbarous brother, not unfourniſhed with the power of ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance; It ſeemed good reaſon that it mooued him to looke vp ſo often, but heere hee ſhewed his great infirmitie, <note place="margin">Iacob fainted in gods pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes. Gen. 32. 28.</note> who did not ſtick to the promiſe of God, which hee had receiued aſſuredlie, <hi>Cum hominibus proeualebis,</hi> that hee ſhould preuaile with men, but did as it maie bee ſaid, ſo much faint by lifting vp his eyes to his Brothers power, which ſhoulde haue beene faſtened vpon the couenant of the Lord, with whom hee preuailed: not that wee condemne his forecaſt, and vigilancie in foreſeeing the daunger that was like to enſue, but that it was likelie, that this often lifting vppe of his eyes, and his loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king ſo longlie, proceeding from a doub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting and quailing heart, which ſhould haue beene eſtabliſhed in the othe which GOD ſware vnto his Grandfather <note place="margin">Gen. 22. &amp; 26. 3. The promiſes entailed to Iacob, ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally.</note> 
                  <hi>Abraham,</hi> and his father <hi>Iſaac,</hi> which was as it weere intayled vnto him ſpirituallie, in the decree of the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie, which decree his Father
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:177190:8"/>
could not alter, as well as he loued <hi>Eſau,</hi> For ſo often as we diſtruſt gods promiſes <note place="margin">Ge. 25. 28.</note> when wee haue vſed the ordinary meane, we derogate from the glorie of God, by calling his credit in queſtion, through our infidelitie, which deſerueth no pittie at his handes, but to vee forſaken. Take <note place="margin">Ge. 3. 12. We muſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware of vnbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeuing harts.</note> heede therefore, that wee haue no euill and unbeleeuing hartes to depart from the liuing God, by lifting vp our eies, and looking ſtill with faithles fearefull hartes vppon the violence of <hi>Eſau,</hi> ſince God hath ſaid to the maintainers of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie, <hi>Non derelinquam ie, nec deſeram</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ioſua.</hi> 1. 5.</note> 
                  <hi>te,</hi> I will not leaue thee, nor forſake thee.</p>
               <p>Wee will proceede to the expoſition of the other member of the firſt part, before wee goe farther, that in the explication they maie bee vſed Ioynt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie. That which followeth therefore conteineth the pomp and power of <hi>Eſau: And beholde, Eſau came, and with him foure hundred men.</hi> The worde <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iohn.</hi> 1. 36.</note> Beholde, betokeneth demonſtration. As <hi>Iohn</hi> Baptiſt poynted at Chriſt pasſing by with his finger ſaying, <hi>Behold the Lambe of God which taketh awaie
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:177190:8"/>
the ſinnes of the worlde.</hi> Heere is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vnto vs, that <hi>Iacob</hi> diſcribed <hi>Eſau</hi> a farre off comming before hee mette him: which hee might the better doe, becauſe hee came with ſo great a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panie, which did awaite vpon him. Moreouer this worde <hi>Beholde</hi> in the Scripture prepareth attention to ſome ſtrange matter which enſueth. Such Recorick vſed Gods Angell, when hee would declare that <hi>Elizabeth</hi> being both <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luke.</hi> 36.</note> olde and barren, ſhould beare a ſonne: to both theſe vſes it ſerueth in this place.</p>
               <p>It followeth, <hi>Eſau came &amp; with him foure hundred men.</hi> This great retinew <note place="margin">Eſaus reti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>new was of his ſonnes and kindred.</note> of his, as may appeare els where, was of his ſonnes &amp; kindred, which had encrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed vnto him of his Cananitiſh wiues a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Hittites, men of great account, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ge.</hi> 26. 34.</note> dukes, and nobles of the earth, liuing ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertheles of the ſpoile, as many do, which beare their heades full high at this day.</p>
               <p>In our iudgement it may be thought that <hi>Moyſes</hi> mentioning-foure I undred men doth cloſely diſtinguiſh betweene the warlike marching of <hi>Eſau,</hi> and the wearied traueling of ſillie <hi>Iacob,</hi> which was combred with Women, Children
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:177190:9"/>
and cattle, in his iourney. But to come to our purpoſe, wee ſee here the miſerie of <hi>Iacob,</hi> and the pomp, and power of <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſau,</hi> to bee conſidered. <hi>Eſau</hi> martcheth <note place="margin">The miſery of Iacob, the pomp of Eſau.</note> forwards, with what purpoſe wee know not: ſaue that a man may coniecture by the circumſtances, that he came with a purpoſe of reuenge againſt his brother. For that rictous aſſemblie would haue made ante man in <hi>Iacobs</hi> caſe to ſuſpect no leſſe, eſpeciallie conſidering the place whence hee came, euen from among the Heathen. It was verie like that hee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned <note place="margin">Eſau came from among the Heathen.</note> from thence more deformed, then reformed, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerning his malicious mind: As manie of our countrimen haue doone from the other ſide of the Sea, feeding vaine mens fautaſies with Italian gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, Spaniſh faſhions, and french cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſies, and verie ſeruiceable in ſpeach, <hi>A Voſtre commandemente Monſieur:</hi> &amp; are therefore become a by-word vnto the <note place="margin">Deuils in car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate.</note> worlde to bee called Deuils incarnate. To let paſſe that whereof wee haue no certaintie, this troup of men was eaſilie able to ouermatch the wearie, and weak companie of <hi>Iacob:</hi> and who woulde thinke now, ſeeing the great inequalitie
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:177190:9"/>
of their ſtates, but that the birthright and bleſſing which <hi>Iacob</hi> had receiued aboue his brother <hi>Eſau,</hi> was a meere mockerie:</p>
               <p>This no queſtion, is the Iudgement <note place="margin">The iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the fleſh Rom. 9. 8.</note> of the fleſh, which eſteemeth things ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the outward ſhew: but <hi>Iacobs</hi> promiſe was ſpiritual, with which hee held himſelfe well apaied, neither held he himſelfe beguiled, if it were fulfilled in his poſterity, as ſhal be ſhewed in more due place. In the meane while though <hi>Iacob</hi> be deſpiſed, let vs learne with wiſe hearts, to eſteeme of things as they are. For God is not as man: if he promiſe, he promiſeth to the heart of Man. And without faith no man is capable of his promiſe lawfullie, but ſhal bee accomp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table for inſtruction.</p>
               <p>This euer hath beene the condition <note place="margin">Iacob, ment by Chriſtes church deſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed.</note> of <hi>Iacob,</hi> which is to bee ment of Gods Church upon earth, to bee vile in moſt places in the eies of the world, to be an vnderling, to bee toſſed from poſt to pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lor in all the members of the ſame, which might bee prooued by manie teſtimonies and examples, from <hi>Abel</hi> to Chriſt, and from Chriſt to this daie: but it were to
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:177190:10"/>
carry ſtickes into the wodde, and to ſet up a candle where the ſun ſhineth. On the other ſide, <hi>Eſau,</hi> whereby is ment, the <note place="margin">Eſau termed the Diuels Church.</note> Diuels Church: for we purpoſe to dwell a while in both the branches of this co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon: for in ſuch matter of teaching wee haue the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> for a warrantic; <note place="margin">Gal 4. 24. The congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation of the wicked are mighue.</note> and therefore we may ſay, that the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregations of the vngodly are mightie, the worlde goeth on their ſide, they eate the fat of the land, they haue the beſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferment, and offices, they liue at eaſe, they aile nothing, &amp; yet they can ſcarce afforde <hi>Iacob</hi> the bare breathing of the aire. In <note place="margin">Sam. 2. 7.</note> this worlde they ſuffer no pleaſant thing to paſſe by them vntaſted, their Kyne caſt <note place="margin">Iob. 21. 10.</note> no Calues, their Children daunce in the ſtreets, they drink wine in carued bowls, <note place="margin">Amos. 6. 4 5. 6. 7.</note> they ſtretch their limmes vpon beds of Iuory: But none of them remember the calamity of <hi>Ioſeph. Iacob</hi> is maliced, yea <note place="margin">Iacob mali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced.</note> 
                  <hi>Eſau</hi> will come againſt him with foure hundred men. It was ſo then, and is ſo now: we haue iuſtified our fathers in all their crueltie. Gods Church is made a Stockfiſh amongſt them, &amp; hir Children are ſent home by weepeing Croſſe. It is <note place="margin">1. Cor. 1. 26.</note> no maruel therefore that <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>Not
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:177190:10"/>
many wiſe after the fleſhe, not many mighty, not many noble are called.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And here by the way we haue to look in <note place="margin">Iud. 3. 7. The wrath of God againſt the Church of the Iſraelites.</note> (as in a glas moſt clear) how the church of the Iſraelites forgotte the Lord their god, &amp; ſerued ſerued <hi>Balaam</hi> &amp; <hi>Aſtaroth,</hi> &amp; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the wrath of the lord was kindled a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Iſrael,</hi> &amp; he ſold the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> into the hands of <hi>Cuſan</hi> King of <hi>Meſopotamia.</hi> Againe <note place="margin">Iud. 4.</note> the Church of the Iſraelits did wickedly in the ſight of the Lord, and therefore the Lorde ſolde them into the hands of <hi>Iabin</hi> King of <hi>Canaan.</hi> God and his Chriſt be as mighty &amp; ſtrong at this hour, as when his word was preached in the Churches of <hi>Goletta,</hi> in <hi>Tunes,</hi> in <hi>Cyprus,</hi> in <hi>Rhodes,</hi> in <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> in <hi>Iudea,</hi> in <hi>Macedonia, Ponthus, Bithinia, Cicilia, Phrygia, Greece, Egypt,</hi> and the endes of the worlde. But <hi>Eſau</hi> came againſt <hi>Iacob</hi> with foure hundred men, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>field Chriſtian mens handes, and filled their fingers full of iniquitie, their lippes ſpake vntruethes, &amp; their tongus vttered wickednes, <hi>Eſau</hi> &amp; his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pany haue made <note place="margin">Eſah hath made chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians forget God.</note> chriſtians to forget the lord, &amp; ſerued <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laam</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> &amp; <hi>Aſtaroth</hi> of <hi>Florence.</hi> They be either ſuperſtitious idolaters, or
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:177190:11"/>
Godleſſe and thanckleſſe Epicures, and worldlings. <hi>Eſau</hi> his companie came a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Iacob</hi> to praie, and ſpoile, to fill the land ful of Uſurers, bribers, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tortioners, and the Sea ful of Pirats, and robbers: therefore the Lord hath hid his face from <hi>Iacob,</hi> to be ment the Church of Chriſt, and hath ſolde into <hi>Eſau</hi> the <hi>Turkes</hi> hands, not onely <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Chriſtian kingdomes ſubdued by the Turke.</note> 
                  <hi>Cyprus, Goletta, Moldauia, Bulgaria, Hungaria, Strygonyum</hi> and <hi>Buda,</hi> but alſo hath opened thereby to the <hi>Turke,</hi> Chriſtendome both by Sea and by land. No great iourney hath the <hi>Turke</hi> from <hi>Buda</hi> to <hi>Saxonie,</hi> and <hi>Demnarke:</hi> and how nigh the <hi>Danes,</hi> and <hi>Saxons</hi> bee to <note place="margin">The Turke hath no farre Journey to England.</note> England, Engliſhmen ſhould remember. No great Journey hath the <hi>Turke,</hi> from <hi>Goletta</hi> to <hi>Spayne:</hi> and howe nigh <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niardes</hi> bee to Englande, Engliſhmen cannot forgette. Yet <hi>Iacobs</hi> familie in England wanteth not a Captaine and heade, but hath a good and gracious go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernor, <note place="margin">We haue a gracious cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine and Head in Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</note> whom God preſerue with Gods word and Sacramentes, Peace, plentie, and all good things. But it was not e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough for the <hi>Iſraelits</hi> to ſaie, <hi>Templum Domini:</hi> nor for the <hi>Iewes, Domine, Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne:</hi>
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:177190:11"/>
nor for the <hi>Romaniſts,</hi> The Church, the Church: nor for vs, The Goſpell, the Goſpell: but we muſt doe works worthy of the worde, and worthie of the Goſpel. <hi>Ferte igitur fructus,</hi> bring forth there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <note place="margin">Ma. 3. 8.</note> the fruites &amp;c. Well, wee reade that <hi>Eſau</hi> came againſt <hi>Iacob,</hi> and with him four hundred men. Whereby we ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that the congregation of the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked and vngodlie are manie and migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, they haue the world at will, they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member not the miſerie of <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> and <note place="margin">Ioſephs miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie forgotten.</note> 
                  <hi>Iacob</hi> is maliced. And can this great wickednes eſcape vengeance: no truely. For whoſoeuer is guiltie, &amp; ſo perſiſteth, ſhall heare his owne condemnation. The very ground groneth vnder the burden <note place="margin">Eſay. 26. 21.</note> of Tyrantes, and ſhal diſcloſe hir blood, and hide hir ſlaine no more.</p>
               <p>And heere wee haue to conſider, how much of hir owne blood and of the blood <note place="margin">Rome came by her regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment by ſhed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of blood.</note> of ſtrangers did <hi>Rome</hi> ſhed before ſhee came to the regiment, and rule of the worlde: but the blood of Gods Martyrs which they haue perſecuted crieth for ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance to God, euen as the blood of righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous <hi>Abel,</hi> which was ſlaine by wicked <hi>Kaine,</hi> Oh God of heauen neuer plague
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:177190:12"/>
vs again with that infernal Synagogue of <hi>Rome:</hi> if there be any Chriſtian heart doe wiſh it, God open that heart to the ſincere acknowledging of his Goſpel, and <note place="margin">Rome could continew hir perſecution no longer then God had appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</note> the embracing of his mercies in Chriſt Jeſus. But when the time of their tiran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie and perſecution was ended, no longer or farther could they go, as the captiuity of <hi>Babylon</hi> was appointed to continew threeſcore &amp; ten yeers, &amp; ſo to ceaſe.</p>
               <p>And when <hi>Rome</hi> had aſpired to the rule and gouernment of the world, what ſhameful oppreſſion raigned on the earth, their owne Chronicles make mention. This did the Prophete <hi>Eſaiah</hi> foreſee, ſaying, <hi>Quid vobis accidit, atteritis popu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum meum, &amp; facies pauperum commolit is?</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Eſay. 3. 15.</note> What haue you to do, that you beate my people in peeces, and grinde the faces of the poor (ſaith the lord?) <hi>Audite quoeſo ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pita Iacob, &amp; Duces Iſrael, nonne veſtrum</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Mich. 3. 1.</note> 
                  <hi>erat ſcire iudicium?</hi> Heare, I pray you, you heads of <hi>Iacob,</hi> and you Princes of <hi>Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ell,</hi> ſhould not you know Judgement's But they hate the good, and loue the euil: they pluck off the skins from them, &amp; the fleſh from their bones, they choppe them as ſmall as fleſh to the potte. Theſe were
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:177190:12"/>
the complaints of <hi>Iſaias</hi> &amp; <hi>Micha</hi> in their times. If they had liued with vs, what <note place="margin">The com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint of the prophet Eſay, and Micha.</note> ſhal we think we ſhould haue hard at their handes? <hi>Iacob</hi> hauing experience of his brothers malice, lifteth vp his head feare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fullie, looking ſtil for more anger: For the burnt Child feareth the fire.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Dauid</hi> after <hi>Saul</hi> had darted his Jaue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lin at him, fled from his tiranny. And gods <note place="margin">1 Sam. 18. 11. &amp; 23. 43. Gods church perſecuted looketh for greater trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles.</note> Church amongeſt vs hauing alreadie ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteined many great iniuries, lifteth vp and looketh with great feare &amp; trembling for ſorer oppreſſion. But leaſt any ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhould think that ſhe complaineth &amp; lifteth vp hir eies w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out a cauſe, let vs conſider by theſe fewe particulars, the wrong that is done to <hi>Iſrael.</hi> The ſouls of the people are moſt precious iewels &amp; tenderly to be kept (for <note place="margin">Actes. 20. 28. The ſoules of the people being preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous iewels are betraied.</note> they coſt chriſt his life) they are neglected, nay they are betraied into the handes of the Diuell. Although <hi>Eſau</hi> himſelfe (I mean the <hi>Pope)</hi> be baniſhed by a moſt no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble &amp; vertuous prince, yet the ſtincke that he hath left behinde him hath to this day infected many.</p>
               <p>There are ſome that deny him in word, <note place="margin">Vnfaithfull proteſtantes. Ephe. 4. 18.</note> and yet build vp his kingdom: For is not ignorance the pillor of his kingdom? Hath
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:177190:13"/>
not the blindnes of our harts bin the chie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt weapon, with which he hath driuen ſo <note place="margin">Ignorance the pillor of the Popes kingdome.</note> manie of vs before him, as Oreu to the ſlaughter? Why then is <hi>Iacob</hi> (we meane gods Church) with domb dogs, I meane domb Deuils, ſo iniuriouſly burdened: I cal the ignorant, &amp; domb miniſters, domb dogs, &amp; not I, but the <hi>Prophet Iſaias.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eſa.</hi> 56. 10.</note> And we call the ignorant vſurping Miniſters which fil vp the meaſure of their ſins, with licencious life, domb Deuils, which can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be caſt out, without faſting, &amp; prayer. <note place="margin">Gods church burdned with dumb dogges. Mark. 9. 29.</note> For wherin are they not become vnto vs in ſteed of <hi>Belial?</hi> Alas, alas, poore <hi>Iacob,</hi> how doſt thou mourn in thy aſhes: why do men cal thee bleſſed, ſince thou art yet ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect to the oppreſſion of <hi>Eſau?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Let vs mark, I pray you, the power of theſe Traditionaries: <note place="margin">Eſau hinde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation of Iacob.</note> they come out euen to the number of 400, to hinder the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation of <hi>Iacob:</hi> and if any be deſirous to know the cauſe why, <hi>Demetrius</hi> the ſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer-Smith ſhall aunſweare for them all, Sirs you know, by this craft, we haue our goods. <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Acts.</hi> 19. 25.</note> Let <hi>Eſaus</hi> Traditionaries deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cend into the conſideration of their Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons, which they ſo mightily defende, then ſhall they perceaue in ſteede of reforming
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:177190:13"/>
malefactors, diſcipline bought out, and <note place="margin">Diſcipline bought out for mony. Hoſe. 4. 8.</note> ſo in the corruption of their conſciences, making marchandizes of ſin, <hi>Peccata po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puli mei comedunt, <hi>They eate vppe the ſinnes of my people, &amp; lift their hands to iniquitie.</hi>
                  </hi> And is this the friendlie intertainment of <hi>Iacob?</hi> With what face dare they looke vpon the Sunne, which haue let ſouls to farme to the Diuel: Let vs ſpeak the trueth, and lie not: we ſtand euen now in the preſence of God, who wil not ſuffer vs to eſcape vnpuniſhed, if we ſpeak of the roote of bitterneſſe like <hi>Eſau</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Heb. 12. 15. Ioſ. 7. 15. A excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicate thing in the land.</note> It is ſaid, there is a exco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>municate thing, and before that excommunicate thing be taken away, we ſhall not be able to ſtand againſt our enimies. what is that pyonder Antichriſtian <hi>Eſau,</hi> &amp; that foule Dragon <note place="margin">Re. 9. 10. 11. Abaddon of Rome with his locuſtes.</note> 
                  <hi>Abaddon</hi> with his locuſtes hath left his taile behinde him, and is not the ſting in the taile: That is true, the wounded of Gods people ſhall ſhew you. That which ſuperſtition cannot doe becauſe it is in a great part weakened, (the Lorde haue the glorie for the ſame) Sathan hath co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted <note place="margin">Sathans au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority.</note> to the ſpirite of Ambition, &amp; Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uetouſnes to accompliſh. The time was when <hi>Iacob</hi> came in the name of <hi>Eſau,</hi> &amp; <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gen.</hi> 17. 18.</note>
                  <pb n="18" facs="tcp:177190:14"/>
was bleſſed, but now is <hi>Eſau</hi> ſtopped in with the ſmooth handes of <hi>Iacob,</hi> and is <note place="margin">Eſau bleſſed, Iacob curſed.</note> curſed.</p>
               <p>The time was when many ſeemed to melt at the miſery of <hi>Sion.</hi> The time is, when the ſelfeſame men, ly frozen in their <note place="margin">Zoph. 1. 12. The miſerie of Sion.</note> dregges in <hi>Babylon.</hi> When the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of Sathan began to increaſe after the deceaſe of Godly paſtors in the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitiue <note place="margin">Sathans king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed.</note> church, idle and prophane men v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurped the place and tooke to themſelues condemnation by violence. Theſe men beeing both vnable, and vnwilling them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues to execute their office in teaching the people, put ouer their charge to ſtocks and ſtones, &amp; dombe Idols. To this end <hi>Gregories error</hi> pleaſed them wel, That Images are Lay-mens books. <note place="margin">Pope Grego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie his error.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Thus wrapped they mens hearts in ignorance, &amp; with the price of their Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry <note place="margin">The papiſtes enriched by Idolatric.</note> built them Pallaces, which threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the heauens. Conſider therefore, that Ererciſe, and diligence, in hearing, &amp; rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of Gods worde taught, or preached, bringeth men from ignorance, And again Ererciſe &amp; diligence cauſeth men to haue a credit in Religion, whether it be true or <note place="margin">What bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth religion into credite.</note> falſe: for it neuer taketh place and root in
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:177190:14"/>
the people without diligence, as it is to be perceaued in the Actes &amp; geſts done in the time of <hi>Ieroboam,</hi> &amp; <hi>Roboam</hi> Kings <note place="margin">3. <hi>Reg</hi> 12. <hi>The Maſſe brought into credit.</hi>
                  </note> of <hi>Iſrael</hi> &amp; <hi>Iuda.</hi> What brought the maſſe and al other Idolatry into eſtimation, but daily ſaieng &amp; preaching therof, with ſuch laud and praiſe, that the moſt ignorants knew what a Maſſe was worth? Fifteene Maſſes in a Church were not enough for the Preſtes of <hi>Baal</hi> to bee ſaid daily: And ſhould one Sermon in a daie be too much for a godly &amp; euangelicall Miniſter? But here ſome will ſay, labor is left and mens buſinesly vndone.</p>
               <p>Surely this is ungodly to bee ſpoken: <note place="margin">The ſayings of the vngod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly.</note> for thoſe that beare the people in hand of ſuch thinges, know very well, that there was neither labor, cares, needs, neceſſities nor any thing els, that could heretofore keep thé from maſſe, though it had binſaid at four of the clock in the morning. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore wee may perceaue the people were contented to leeſe more labour, and ſpend more time then, to goe to the Devil, than <note place="margin">More labor ſpent to go to the Diuel, thá to come to God.</note> now to come to god: wherefore where daily praier is ſaid, not only in churches, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo in priuate houſes, the Parentes, Mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, Children and family ſhall finde ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uauntage
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:177190:15"/>
and gaine thereby at the yeeres <note place="margin">Daily praier in priuate houſes.</note> end, though they hear daily a ſermon, mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and euening praier euery day in the weake.</p>
               <p>Thus did <hi>Adam</hi> ſerue god, after he was <note place="margin">Gen. 4. Adam ſerued God.</note> called to repentance, and in ſteed of a mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter, did teach his children, and familie, firſt to know their ſauiour, and to ſerue god, in true faith, as witneſſeth the oblati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of his obedient ſon <hi>Abel. Seth</hi> and <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noch</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Seth &amp; Enoch called on god. Gen. 5. Heb. 11. Gen. 6. Noah the preacher of righteouſnes.</note> in like manner ſerued God, for it is written of them, that they began to make inuocation to the name of the Lord.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Noah</hi> with his children &amp; family was not onely ſaued from drouning, but hath this true title to be called the preacher of righteouſnes.</p>
               <p>What ſhould we ſpeake of <hi>Abraham, Iſaac, Iacob</hi> &amp; <hi>Loth,</hi> which made inuoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion <note place="margin">Gen. 11. 12. 47. Heb. 11. Iacob &amp; Loth preached gods word.</note> to the name of the lord, and in ſteed of preachers, taught the word of god them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, and retained the true faith ſurelie grounded vpon the ſaid word, and by good example of life, and doctrine, left the ſame to their families &amp; poſterities: but when, as we haue ſaid, in the kingdom of <hi>Sathan</hi> prophane men vſurped the places of god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly men, in the primitiue Church, and had
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:177190:15"/>
wrapped mens harts in ignorance and I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolatry, <note place="margin">Mens harts were wrapped in Idolatrie.</note> they maintained <hi>Eſaus</hi> Traditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onaries with the gaines thereof: but now (thanks bee giuen to God) in theſe latter times we haue eaſed <hi>Iacobs</hi> ſhoulders of ſuch burdens, and haue well purged our Churches from ſuch abominations.</p>
               <p>But yet muſt it needes bee ſaid, that <note place="margin">Many igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant miniſters of the mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt ſort. Reg. 12 31.</note> there are put in the places of godly paſtors many an ignorant, &amp; diſſolute perſon: and our miniſters for the moſt part, are as the prieſts of <hi>Ieroboam,</hi> euen of the loweſt of the people. And this we haue don, leaſt we <note place="margin">Wee loue not to haue our faultes repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued.</note> ſhould hear hard things, leaſt our ambiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and couetouſnes ſhould be reproued: and why ſhould we not ſpeak plainly and tel the truth: for filthy lucre ſake we haue committed Sacrilege, nay wee will ſaie <note place="margin">Sacrilege for Lucre ſake. Soules mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered.</note> more, we haue murdered the ſoules of our brethren. Will anie bodie put vs to our proofe: Who wil then ſeek for reformati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on when it is proued:</p>
               <p>Many are patrones of benefices, &amp; they <note place="margin">Benefices ſold to Symoniſtes for mony.</note> ſel that for mony to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that wil giue moſt, among the wicked <hi>Symoniſts</hi> men of litle account, leſſe vnderſtanding, &amp; leaſt conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of al: &amp; yet they ſay we are no Church <note place="margin">Church-rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers.</note> robbers, and we murther no ſoules.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="22" facs="tcp:177190:16"/>
Noblemen and men of worſhip (or els they bear lies) write their letters vnto the Biſhops for admitting of vnworthy per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons to the miniſterie, yea ſuch as are of <note place="margin">Vnworthy perſons ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to the miniſterie.</note> the worſer, and baſer ſort, farre vnmeete for that calling: neither learned, godly, or zealous, but couet the roomes of godlie paſtors, to lead an idle life, and for coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſnes <note place="margin">Chriſts Church fraught with vnlearned hierlings.</note> ſake they may bee well tearmed good cheap hirelings. <hi>Iacobs</hi> church is at this daie ſo fraught with them, that the learned which deſire the office to ſet forth the glorie of God, and the edifieng of his people <note place="margin">No place for the godly and learned in Chriſtes church.</note> in the right knowledge of his word, can haue no places to increaſe their ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lents, vnleſſe they wil be hirelings for ten pounds by the yeere, although the liuing be worth to the parſon or farmor, and hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred pounds by the yeere.</p>
               <p>The common people ſay, that Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall men haue too much, they keepe no <note place="margin">The murmor of the people againſt the ſpiritualtie.</note> hoſpitality, they neither preach nor teach after they haue liuings, they become co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uetous. They ware rich, &amp; wil not ariſe out of their neſts, which they thinke they haue built in a rocke. Thoſe that ſhould <note place="margin">Pſal. 74. 9.</note> be ouer-ſeers of theſe, lie idle, not looking to their charge, they ſend foorth manie
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:177190:16"/>
to waite vpon <hi>Eſau,</hi> but fewe to wait vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>Iacob.</hi> They which haue the places of puniſhing ſinne, haue learned their leſſon of the horſle aches two daughters. A man <note place="margin">Pro. 30. 15.</note> may trauel ſome way, &amp; find not a prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher <note place="margin">Preaching de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caied.</note> in fifteene Pariſhes, nor yet any Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter able to expound fire woordes of the Scripture. Haue we not then iuſt cauſe, to take vp the ould complaint of <hi>Moſes</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Exod. 32. 21.</note> againſt <hi>Aaron? what did the people vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thee, that thou haſt brought ſo great ſinne vpon them?</hi> All theſe miſeries of <hi>Iacob</hi> not withſtanding, caſt vp your eyes about, and you ſhall ſee a pompe like the pomp of <hi>Eſau.</hi> What they were in times paſt, that maketh no matter to vs: God <note place="margin">Gal. 2. 6. Ezech. 33. 12.</note> accepteth no mans perſon, their oulde works are forgotten. If they diſcontinue I ſay many of them now, whether of <hi>Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob</hi> or no, wee can not tell. The Lord knoweth who are his. But this wee are ſure of, they lift vp themſelues againſt <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael,</hi> muſling the mouth of the Oxen that treade out the corne: and comming out <note place="margin">1. Cor. 1. 9. Pſal. 9. 12.</note> with foure hundred men, ſome dumbe dogges, ſome filthie Cananites, which <note place="margin">The procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings of Iacob hindered.</note> haue caſt in their lots among theeues, to hinder the proceeding of innocent <hi>Iacob.</hi>
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:177190:17"/>
Will not God haue all theſe things in minde, when he maketh Inquiſition for bloud: <hi>Can not hee iudge through the</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Iob. 12. 13.</note> 
                  <hi>darke clouds?</hi> Yes, yes, God hath not ſo conteinned the lifting up of <hi>Iacobs</hi> eies, nor colerated the wayes of the ſcornfull, that he ſhould returne to viſite them, and take them as he findeth them. Neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe let us pray for them, euen the prayer of the Prophet, <hi>Giue them, Lord: What</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Hoſe. 9. 14.</note> 
                  <hi>ſhalt thou giue them? A barren womb, and drie breſts: Let the children periſh for the ſinnes of their fathers.</hi> As for E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſau himſelf, let him drinke, and be drunk, and ſtumble, and fall, and riſe no more. It is little enough that to ſome we ſeeme more ſharpe, than the matter requireth. But I would to God we were more tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched with the ruine of <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> that <hi>Iacob,</hi> I meane Gods Church, might finde redreſſe for theſe iniuries.</p>
               <p>Who is he amongeſt men, or what is <note place="margin">A ſimilitude of the church.</note> his name, which hauing one onely daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, moſt vertuous, &amp; moſt beautiful, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orned with moſt excellent qualities, the ſtaffe of hir fathers comfort, being betro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed to a worthie king of great eſtate, would not bee drowned with teares, and
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:177190:17"/>
ſwallowed up with unmeaſureable ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>romes, if ſhee were violently taken from him, and given to a miſcreant baſtarde, Iothſome and deformed perſon, being in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected with all manner of moſt filthie, and contagious diſeaſes? And is not this the caſe of gods church? <hi>How glorious is the</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 45. 15. Eph. 5. 27. 2. Cor. 11. 2. Chriſts church co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters charge 1. Sam. 4. 11.</note> 
                  <hi>kinges Daughter within? She hath nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſpot nor wrinkle:</hi> ſhe is betrothed to Chriſt: And by prockſie he hath co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted her to the charge of his true miniſters. But lift your eies, &amp; look, behold, I ſay, &amp; weep. For the arke is taken fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the <hi>Leuit:</hi> the ſpouſe of Chriſt is committed to the hands of filthie, uncleane, and brutiſh per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons: <note place="margin">Reuelat. 9. 3.</note> Iuskiſh locuſts are ingendred of the ſmoke of baſtard diſcipline, which are as thornes to our eies, and ſcorpions to out ſides. The ſheeprives ſtand by, and looke on, yet none of them ſtretcheth forth his arme to pluck the lamb fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the <hi>Eagle,</hi> nor the <hi>Turtle Doue</hi> out of the hande of the <note place="margin">Pſal. 74. 19.</note> beaſt. And now wee beſeech you giue ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, are the tears of <hi>Iſrael</hi> as the tears of an unconſtant woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>? Or hath be not iuſt cauſe to complain? But to what purpoſe are the iniuries of the Church laide be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <note place="margin">The iniuries of the church laid before vs,</note> you, &amp; compared with the iniuries of
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:177190:18"/>
                  <hi>Iacob?</hi> Forſooth to this end, that like as the iniuries alreadie offered to <hi>Iacob,</hi> made him to fear farther violence, &amp; ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to lift up his eies, and look when <hi>Eſau</hi> came: So it might appeare that the iniu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries offered to Gods Church maie iuſtlie make it to feare farther vengeance from God, and violence from men: and therefore to lift up their eies, and looke when the Pope himſelf ſhal come. For let him come <note place="margin">A number of the Popes knightes dub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain his king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome.</note> to morowe, and wee haue dubbed a num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of doltes for his purpoſe: He ſhall need to alter neither the men, nor their or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders: and if wee haue made idle paſtors, hath not Gods church reaſon to lift up hir eies to ſee, when the Idols themſelves ſhal follow?</p>
               <p>If we varniſh his ſtyrrops, wil we neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect his ſadle? If wee be ſo deſirous of his diſcipline, wil we make daintie of his doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine?</p>
               <p>The <hi>Turk</hi> keepeth himſelfe to his Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caran, the <hi>Iew</hi> to his Talmud, or Kabala, &amp; the <hi>Pope</hi> to his Portuiſe. But if gods <note place="margin">The true church of god accuſed of ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gularitic.</note> church cleaue to the ſinglenes of the word, refuſing mixture, and ſeeke a ſervice and adminiſtration thereafter, ſhe is then ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed of ſingularitie, How ſay you nowe?
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:177190:18"/>
do not theſe things giue <hi>Iacob</hi> good cauſe to lift up his eies and to looke when <hi>Eſau</hi> ſhould come with four hundred men? Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue me, beleeue me, if any Magiſtrate ſhould goe about to colour theſe thinges, but not with the couering of gods ſpirite, and ſay, what maketh this to vs? we maie very well ſay againe, What make they then in the places of government in the Church of Chriſt?</p>
               <p>Therefore let the godly lift vp the eies of their harts to God, and pray vnto him, from whom nothing is hid, that there may be a zealous reformation of <hi>Iacobs</hi> trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, <note place="margin">We muſt pray for the refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of Chriſtes Church.</note> and griefes, which is to be feared wil not be, unles we ceaſe from carnal goſpel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, oppreſſion of the poore, couetouſnes, earthly mindes, fleſhly Iuſts, and not to be wiſe in our own ſelues, but to ſeeke to be wiſe in the lord. For he is the opener and molliſter of all hartes which hee turneth. Knock therefore, that the lord may open, ſeeke that you may finde, but ſee that you knock, and ſeeke aright.</p>
               <p>The ſame god that opened the bowels of <hi>Moſes</hi> towards his brethre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, giue al his elect pittiful harts towards poore <hi>Iacob,</hi> yea &amp; to our owne ſoules, that we may in
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:177190:19"/>
ſimplicity and rightnes of ſpirites, tacke our powers to the higheſt pin, for the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uancement of gods glory. Let this ſuffice <note place="margin">We ought to lament the miſeries of Chriſtes Church.</note> for the firſt part, concerning the injuries and miſeries of <hi>Iacob,</hi> and the pomp and power of <hi>Eſau:</hi> Now followeth the ſecond part concerning the diſpoſing of <hi>Iacobs</hi> family conteined in theſe wordes.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="part">
               <head>The Second part.</head>
               <p>2 <hi>And he diuided the children to LEAH and RAHEL, and to the two maides: and he put the maids and their Children foremoſt, and LEAH and hir children after, and Rahel, and Ioſeph hindermoſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>HEere is firſt to bee conſidered and obſerued that difference which is <note place="margin">The differece between the faithful &amp; the vnfaithfull. Gen. 31. 1.</note> found between the vnfaithful &amp; them that feare god with a confidence aſſured in his promiſes. For although <hi>Iacob,</hi> otherwiſe feared the violenee of his brother <hi>Eſau,</hi> and bewraied his infirmitie, euen after God had comforted him, by an hoſt of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, and had giuen him victorie in wra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtling: yet was he not amazed nor blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med <note place="margin">Pſa. 5. 5. &amp; 62. 4.</note> god, like the wicked, with curſes and moſt terrible othes, of all fortes: againſt
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:177190:19"/>
who the prophet <hi>Dauid</hi> crieth out ſaieng: <note place="margin">The wicked blaſpheme god, ſwearing curſing, and lieng.</note> 
                  <hi>The vnrighteous ſhall not ſtand in thy ſight, O lord: thou hateſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that work iniquitie. Thou ſhalt deſtroy al the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that ſpeake lies:</hi> but how much more likely is it, that the lord will deſtroy all them that ſpeake blaſphemie, and abuſe his holie name:</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Saul</hi> verily blaſphemed the name of the <note place="margin">1. Reg. 28. 8. Blaſphemers puniſhed.</note> lord, becauſe he called not vpon his name in his extreme miſery, and trouble, but asked counſaile of a <hi>Pithoniſſe,</hi> was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled to kil himſelfe with his own hand, after he had ſeene his people downe right ſlaine by the <hi>Phyliſtines</hi> his enimies, and his ſonnes lie dead in the middeſt of the people.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ananias</hi> &amp; <hi>Saphira</hi> his wife, lied to the <note place="margin">Acts. 5. 3. 10. Lyers puni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed.</note> holy ghoſt, and falling down ſodenly to the ground, go with ſhame enough to the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uel of hel.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Senacherib</hi> ſweareth &amp; blaſphemeth <note place="margin">4. Reg. 18. 30.</note> the name of the eternall God, before the walles in <hi>Ieruſalem:</hi> but anon after hee for his labor was bereſt of his puiſſant ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, and in his owne gods temple ſhot tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough by his ſonne.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Iehoachim</hi> and <hi>Zedechias</hi> both kings
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:177190:20"/>
of <hi>Iuda,</hi> and blaſphemers of gods name, <note place="margin">4. Reg. 24. 20. 4. Reg. 16. 9. &amp; 10.</note> are taken captiues, &amp; ſlain by <hi>Nabucho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>donoſor</hi> king of <hi>Babylo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Achas, Ieſabel,</hi> and the prieſtes of <hi>Baal</hi> are cleane wyped by King <hi>Iehu,</hi> becauſe that they vnder the colour of God &amp; godlines, perſecuted the true religion.</p>
               <p>The man that blaſphemed the name of <note place="margin">Leuit. 24.</note> God, was ouerwhelmed with ſtones to death.</p>
               <p>The which examples of holy ſcripture, as they are terrible, &amp; dreadful, ſo are they written for vs, to conſider, that not the leaſt part of our calamities at theſe daies do happen vnto vs, becauſe of our deteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble lying, curſing, &amp; horrible othes, which few magiſtrats, parents and maiſters do goe about to redreſſe as they ſhoulde doe. <note place="margin">Magiſtrates &amp; Parentes muſt puniſh blaſphemers. Many blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemous peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in theſe daies.</note> Wherefore the name of the liuing god is blaſphemed with paſſing deep, and horri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble othes of al ſortes, and of al ages, ſo that it is verily to bee thought from the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the worlde, was there neuer ſuch blaſphemous people, as are in this wicked age of ours: and therefore are we vered with vnſpeakable and endleſſe troubles. The plague neuer goeth from the houſe <note place="margin">Eccle. 23. 12.</note> of ſwearers: For God is true &amp; cannot ly,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:177190:20"/>
which ſaieth, That they ſhall not eſcape <note place="margin">Exod. 20.</note> ſcotfree, that take his name in vaine. We ſhould then be ſo tru, one of vs to another, and careful to ſay the truth, that our com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication ſhould bee yea, yea, nay, nay. For whatſoeuer is more then this, is ſin. <note place="margin">Mat. 5.</note> The men of our time do not only take the name of God in vaine, but doe of malice blaſphemouſly defile it. It were therfore very godly, not only that the magiſtrates, but alſo parents, and maſters, in euery of <note place="margin">The dutie of houſhoulders.</note> their priuate houſes, would looke to this horrible abuſe of gods name, and ſharplie puniſh thoſe that are accuſtomably giuen to ſwearing, curſing, and lying: and ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerely by good example &amp; liuing, ſet forth the true worſhip of god among their peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, ouer whom they haue charge: Or els, if this may not be obtained at their hands they will bee no worſe nor godleſſe then <hi>Caiphas:</hi> who whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he hard as he thought <note place="margin">Caiphas. Mat. 26. Mark. 14. 10. 18. Luk. 21.</note> blaſphemy againſt the name of god, rent his clothes and cried that the blaſphemor was worthy to die. For aſſuredly vnleſſe Chriſtian magiſtrates, and gouernors of families do not very earneſtly puniſh the <note place="margin">Vngodly houſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holders worſe tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Caiphas.</note> offendors herein: it cannot otherwiſe bee ſaid, but that they are a great deale worſe
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:177190:21"/>
than that wicked <hi>Caiphas.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But now to come againe to the effect of our matter, wee may well perceaue, that <hi>Iacob</hi> although hee was put into a <note place="margin">Iacob in his crouble blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemeth not God.</note> great fear and agony by his brother <hi>Eſaus</hi> comming againſt him with four hundred <hi>men,</hi> yet did hee not by any meanes blas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheme god. or was amazed like the vngod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly: but behaued himſelfe wiſely. deſcreet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly &amp; prudently, in diſpoſing of his family, for the beſt ſafety and aduantage, if ought had betyd him more rigorouſly: wheras the wicked in time of peril are at their wits end, &amp; ſtand amazed like ſtocks, <note place="margin">Iob. 18. 11.</note> or els are driue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> into ſuch brutiſh paſſions, that they be wray their fearfulnes, (ſo far ſeparated from diſcretio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) that they neuer had any great ſtrength. Example hereof we haue in <hi>Ahas,</hi> and his people, who at <note place="margin">Pro. 24. 10. Eſau. 22.</note> the report of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming of <hi>Aram</hi> againſt them, are ſaid to bee moued with feare like the leaues of a tree ſhaken with the mind. It is true that the wiſeman ſaith, <hi>Bleſſed is hee that alwaies maketh him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Prouer. 28. 24.</note> 
                  <hi>afraid.</hi> For if wee acquaint not our ſelues with mortification, and ſet before <note place="margin">We muſt ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaint our ſelues with mortificatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</note> vs the terror of God, to be exerciſed and humbled in the time of peace, and quiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:177190:21"/>
it is to be feared, leſt when the ſtorms of affliction beat vpon vs, we be ſo affrigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted as much ſome ſtrange thing, that wee ſhall not onely bee beereft of patience, the <note place="margin">Patience the principal ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe of faith. Deu. 28. 29.</note> principall exerciſe of faith, whereby wee poſſeſſe our ſaluation: but alſo be diſabled to vſe the ordinary meanes, ſet before vs for our deliuery, without the which wee ſhal not bee able to eſcape the violence of our enemies. Moreouer if this diſpoſing of <hi>Iacobs</hi> family be conſidered, as occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on wilbe giuen by &amp; by, we ſhal perceaue the doubting of the man which we ſpeake of in the beginning. And theſe infirmities <note place="margin">The infirmity of the Fathers not to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed. Gen. 30. 4. 10.</note> of the fathers we muſt not go about to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe, neither in this, neither in that, he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gat children of <hi>Bilhah</hi> and <hi>Dilpah,</hi> his wiues maides, whereof mention is made, nor yet in his plurality of wiues, leaſt that I ſhould iuſtify a piece of clay, and beſides that preferre iniury to many. Yet in one reſpect (although I reioice not in their ſins) ſince God hath ſo ordained that their <note place="margin">Saluation co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſteth only in Gods mercie. 1. Cor. 9. 10.</note> ſaluation ſhould conſiſt in mere mercy, we may reioice that they fel. For example of gods mercy, for in raiſing them which fel in the beginning, is a ſtaf to hold them up, which are now bowed downe with their
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:177190:22"/>
infirmities. Not that man ſhould wound himſelf in hope of this ſalue, but that thoſe which are already wounded and know it, might not be to ſeek of the Chirurgian.</p>
               <p>But to come neer to our purpoſe, <hi>Iacob</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Iacobs diſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and his wiſedome not in fleſhe nor bloud.</note> not withſtanding the fearfulnes of his hart, yet ſhe weth he great diſcretion, and wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom in ordering of his buſines, as one pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to vſe the beſt ordinary meanes that was offered, &amp; to leaue the reſt to the lord, And whence had he this ſtaiednes &amp; wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom in ſo trouble ſome a time: certainlie neither of fleſhe nor blood, but by the gift of God, without which no man can ſtand vpright in the euil day.</p>
               <p>We read in this former chapter howe he prepared himſelfe to this purpoſe with <note place="margin">Man nothing without god. Gen. 32. 9. Iacob prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red himſelfe with humble praier.</note> feruent and humble praier, for that is the tower of the faithful, and the very ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry way, &amp; meanes, whereby god is moued to help vs in our neceſſities: &amp; they which ſeldom vſe it, prouide euil for their faith. Surely the good ſucceſſe, that the Lord gaue <hi>Iacob</hi> here (after the ſaid praier) ſhould encourage vs to enterpriſe nothing before we haue firſt craued the direction of our god, and ſo much the rather, by this example, becauſe it appeareth by the tenor
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:177190:22"/>
of this praier and the politique diſpoſing of his family being compared with that which followed, and ſucceeded, that God <note place="margin">God gaue Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob more tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he asked. Pſal. 79. 13.</note> gaue him more then he durſt either aske, or looke for, ſo plentifully receiued he, his praiers rewarded home againe into his own boſom. Our leſſon by the way is, that when we haue poured out our ſpirites be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God, crauing any thing at his hands, <note place="margin">We muſt reſt in gods proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence.</note> we muſt ſo reſt in his prouidence, that we do neuertheles vſe the ordinary mean, &amp; not lie ſtill preſumptuouſly tempting the Lord, as the maner of ſome is. Thus did <note place="margin">Ioſua. 7.</note> 
                  <hi>Ioſua</hi> work the will of the lord in his bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tel, &amp; the fruite of his labor was the fulfil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of his praier. Yea when we haue an aſſurance of that we aske at the Lordes hands, yet the exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple of <hi>Elias</hi> teacheth vs <note place="margin">1 Reg. 18. 24. Praier doth exerciſe our faith.</note> to pray ſtil, that our faith be not dul, &amp; idle.</p>
               <p>The concluſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of this note is, that if we wil not haue our wiſedome to fail vs, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we moſt neede it, let vs not forget in the <note place="margin">In our trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles we muſt put the Lord in mind of his mercies.</note> ſearefulnes of our harts becauſe of our in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmity, to put the lord in mind of his mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, leaſt when da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger is laid vpon vs, our ſhadowe of wiſdome be ſcattered into the clouds, &amp; we cruſhed vnder <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </p>
               <p>Further more here is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="36" facs="tcp:177190:23"/>
care &amp; love that this holy Patriat <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <note place="margin">The chriſtian love and care of Iacob to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily.</note> had towardes his familie. The malice which was in <hi>Eſau,</hi> he knew wel, was but againſt his own perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. And therfore if his tender love towards his wiues, had not greatlie preuailed w<hi rend="sup">c</hi> him, he might haue taken his flight to eſcape fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the hands of <hi>Eſau:</hi> But he as a louing, &amp; faithful father of a family, did not only carry by it, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo put them in ſuch array, as might beſt beſeem the intertainme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of the lord <hi>Eſau,</hi> or rather might beſt ſerue for the ſafegard of come of their liues, which was kinder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt, by taking their flight, if <hi>Eſau</hi> ſhould aſſault the foremoſt. This chriſtian loue <note place="margin">Iacobs loue to his wines, is wanting in many huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands in theſe daies.</note> of <hi>Iacob</hi> to his wiues, &amp; the godly care to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards his family, is wanting in many in theſe daies, which range abroad not for a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny danger that driveth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but they go to ſeek it. If one that were in autority ſhuld examine many of our young gentlemen, which haue bound the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to the unſeparable knot of holy marriage, what is the cauſe <note place="margin">Vaine trauell.</note> that engliſh ground cannot bear the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: why ſome of them ſhake the buckler in <hi>Paris,</hi> &amp; ſome other walke the ſtreets in <hi>Venis:</hi> &amp; <note place="margin">Like husba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nd <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> they can giue as good account of it, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> wiues which they haue
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:177190:23"/>
left behind them, ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> do of their unchaſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haviour in England. But ſuch marraige is no more honorable than whoredome.</p>
               <p>And here by the waie we may wel con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider, <note place="margin">The vngodly attyre of weo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</note> that <hi>Iacobs</hi> wiues were not appare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, like to our wiues in England in theſe baies, more like Maskers, than Matrons, with heades compaſſed like to Rammes Hornes, and frilled haires, more meet for ſparrowes to make their neſts in, than for chriſtians to wear. If they were wel diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to reade the ſcriptures, they ſhould learn what Saint <hi>Peter</hi> ſpeaketh of wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men-like apparel, ſaying: That womens <note place="margin">1. Pet. 3. 3. 4. 5. 6.</note> apparel ſhould not be outward with broy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded haire, either in putting on of gorgious apparel. But let the hid man which is in the heart, bee without all corruption of a meeke and quiet ſpirite, which ſpirite is before God a thing much ſet by. For after this maner, did the women in the old time which truſted in God, attire themſelves, being obedient to their husbands, euen as <hi>Sara</hi> obeied <hi>Abraham</hi> &amp; called him Lord. <hi>Cyprian</hi> that godlie martyr writeth this <note place="margin">Cyprian ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king againſt the vnſeemly attyre of weo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</note> of women, ſaying. <hi>Qua ſericum &amp; purpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram induunt, Chriſtum induere non poſſunt.</hi> Women that advance themſelues in put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:177190:24"/>
on ſilke, and purple, cannot lightlie put on Chriſt. And againe, <hi>Foemine crines ſuos inficiunt malo proeſagio, capillos enim ſibi flammeos auſpicari non metuunt.</hi> They which colour their heires with red &amp; yel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low begin to prognoſticate of what colour their heads ſhalbe in hel. And farther hee ſaith, <hi>Qui ſe pingunt in hoc ſeculo, aliter qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> creauit Deus, metuant, cum reſurrection is venerit dies, ne artifex creaturam ſnam non cognoſcat.</hi> They which loue to paint them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues here in this world, otherwiſe than God hath created them, let them feare, leaſt when the day commeth of reſurrec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, the creator wil not know them. And for theſe and the like abuſes the lord both puniſh our ſinnes, one with another. Wee may heere in like maner obiect the exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of <hi>Iacob</hi> with the peeuiſh Papiſtes, which uppon forged pretence of conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, haue left their Nature ſoile, their wiues, their children, their families, and haue broken their obedience to their true, lawful, and chriſtian Princeſſe: and when England is to hot for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, are run to rouſt at <hi>Rome.</hi> If <hi>Iacob</hi> had fled, hee had fled from <hi>Eſau,</hi> a tyrant. But they in fleeing <note place="margin">1. Sam. 15. 10. 1. Reg. 11. 4.</note> are become like to <hi>Ieroboam,</hi> which fled
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:177190:24"/>
from peaceable <hi>Salomon,</hi> to the <hi>Egypti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans.</hi> But they haue a vow in <hi>Hebron</hi> like <hi>Abſolon</hi> a traitor to his own father. And can there bee a more vnconſcionable act, then to break the loialty of true ſubiectes towards ſo louing a princeſſe, &amp; to make themſelues ſlaues to a infamous ſtranger? we may maruell with what forehead they may plead conſcience any longer. The maner, why <hi>Moſes</hi> doth ſo diligently re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port the order of this array, is, that wee might vnderſtand whom <hi>Iacob</hi> was moſt <note place="margin">Iacob deſired to ſaue ſome.</note> deſirous to ſaue (if any danger had bin) for the foremoſt were in moſt danger, and likeſt to be ſlaine firſt, if <hi>Eſau</hi> had drawne <note place="margin">Gen. 32. 8.</note> ſword againſt them: and therefore he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clareth that the twoo Maides with their children were put in the Fronttire, and <hi>Leah,</hi> and hir children next, and <hi>Rahel</hi> &amp; hir children hindermoſt. Onely this note is here to be giuen, that when he thought to prouide for the eſcape of ſome, <hi>Ioſeph</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Ioſeph moſt precious in Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cobs eyes.</note> his yongeſt ſonne, and the only ſon of <hi>Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hel</hi> was moſt precious in his eies, and (no doubt) he was co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>forted in the hope which he had of him, euen when he was yet but a child: and therefore placed he him with his mother hindermoſt, that hee might eſcape
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:177190:25"/>
with the firſt. Our inſtruction out of this example is twofold. Firſt we learn not to <note place="margin">Wee muſt not be deſperate in troubles.</note> caſt off al care of buſines, though thinges go not forward as we would haue them, for that were to be deſperate: but to do the beſt we can to ſaue ſome, though there be no hope to ſaue all. <hi>Iacob</hi> looketh not to ſaue all, yea, hee feareth to loſe the moſt part: yet doth he not ſet all at ſixe and ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, as one without care, or counſel; but hath a reſpect to his poſterity after him, <note place="margin">Iacob hath a reſpect to his poſteritie. Ioſ. 14. 23.</note> expecting to himſelfe nothing but preſent death. Likewiſe <hi>Moyſes,</hi> although the Lord told him flatly, that none of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple which he brought out of <hi>Egypt</hi> ſhould enter into the land of promiſe, but <hi>Caleb</hi> and <hi>Ioſua,</hi> thought not he had loſt his wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and long trauel among the reſt. For he knew that in time God could accompliſh his promiſe, much vnlike to thoſe peeuiſh ſpirits, which if the Lord follow not their <note place="margin">Peeuiſh pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtes.</note> humor, bid him take al (as it is in the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerbe.) And the prophet ſheweth, that the <note place="margin">Iſay. 1. 9.</note> reſeruing of a remnant maketh vs that we are not deſtroied, as <hi>Sodom,</hi> nor con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed <note place="margin">Sodom. Gomorrah.</note> like <hi>Gomorra.</hi> Our other leſſon is, that they which are guides, eſpecially go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernors which ſhould be as nourſefathers
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:177190:25"/>
and nourſe mothers: not to put the wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keſt <note place="margin">Gouernours ſhould be nurſe fathers and nurſe mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.</note> to the worſt, but to prouide carefullie for <hi>Ioſeph.</hi> But now the daies are come a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain that <hi>Ioſeph</hi> is carried away from his father, &amp; ſold into <hi>Egypt</hi> by his brethren, where they caſt him into priſon. Not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding his bleſſing which his father <hi>Iacob</hi> gaue vnto him, was alſo repeted by <hi>Moyſes,</hi> as he then had a carnal fruiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of it, ſo ſhal be in the latter times (in his poſterity) obtaine a ſpirituall poſſeſſion of the ſame: Namely, the bleſſing of God, which dwelt in the buſh, ſhal be vpon the <note place="margin">Gen. 49. 26. Deut. 33. 16.</note> head of <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> and vpon the toppe of the head of him, which was ſeparated fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his brethren. If it bee demanded why <hi>Iudas</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Why Iudas was not pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced hinder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt.</note> was not rather placed hindermoſt for his ſafetie, ſeeing that the ſcepter was his by promiſe, and ſeing that of his tribe ſhould come the Meſſias as appeareth in his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſie vpon his death bed, the anſwere is <note place="margin">Gen. 49. 10.</note> eaſie, for as per this was vnknown to <hi>Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob</hi> himſelfe, who had not the reuelation before he was towards his death.</p>
               <p>Nowe to the laſt note of this ſecond part: you ſhall obſerue the notable go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment of <hi>Iacob,</hi> howe reuerend a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of a family wee may gather him to
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:177190:26"/>
haue bene, by this place, and of how great <note place="margin">The notable gouernment of Iacob.</note> autority in al his houſhold. You haue hard how they all went in great danger of their liues. In which caſes euery one of vs, is giuen to ſhift for our ſelues, though it be to the breach of obedience. It is mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uel therfore, that they ſtroue not who ſhuld go hindermoſt, and that euery one coueted not the place of moſt ſafety. Surely in that they were obedient, &amp; ſtood in ſuch array as he thought good to ſet them, there is a notable preſident vnto vs of his pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, &amp; autority, which had trained them vp to this tractablenes: and in them com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendable <note place="margin">A notable ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience.</note> obedience, which quietly kept their places aſſigned without brawling or contention.</p>
               <p>The like example was notable before <note place="margin">Gen. 17. 23. Abrahams fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily obeied him. 1. Reg. 2. 3. 4.</note> in his grandfather <hi>Abraham,</hi> to whom al his ſeruantes obeied and were content to haue their foreskinnes cut, which was a grieuous wound in the fleſh, when cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion was ordained. Contrariwiſe <hi>Eli</hi> the high prieſt his two ſons <hi>Hophni</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Elies ſonnes obeied him not, and are ſlaine.</note> and <hi>Phinees,</hi> becauſe they obeied not their fathers monition, when he rebuked them for their wickednes, for lying with ſtra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge women, which waited at the doore of
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:177190:26"/>
the tabernacle of witnes were both ſlaine by the <hi>Philiſtines</hi> their enemies. <hi>Ely</hi> alſo <note place="margin">Elie plagued for not corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting his ſonnes.</note> himſelfe becauſe he did not ſharply puniſh and correct his ſonnes for their wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, &amp; diſobedience, but did ſeem to winck at their ſins, ſaying, Sons, how is it that I heare ſuch report of you, that yee make the lords people to treſpaſſe againſt him: What became of <hi>Ely</hi> for omitting pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment? Surely when he hard the ark of the Lord was taken by the <hi>Philiſtines,</hi> he fel from a ſtoole and brake his neck. <hi>Hoc ſcriptum eſt ad noſtram doctrinam:</hi> Theſe things are written for our learning: And <note place="margin">Parents muſt be reuerend, to be reueren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced.</note> that maiſters, and parents ſhould learne by the example of the two godly fathers, to be reuerend, that they may be reueren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced: and by <hi>Ely</hi> and his ſonnes to miniſter ſharp diſcipline for notable offences. And let them both by nurture, example and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion, go in and out before their family, that they haue them obedient in al the wil of the Lord. For it muſt be obſerued, that becauſe both <hi>Abraham</hi> and <hi>Iacob</hi> went <note place="margin">Gen. 18. 19. Abraham and Iacob did gods will. Num. 22. 23.</note> about the wil of their God, therefore they enclined the hartes of their family to obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience. Otherwiſe, the very <hi>Aſſe,</hi> whereon <hi>Balaam</hi> rode, was diſobedient vnto him,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:177190:27"/>
becauſe he went about wickednes, &amp; him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe diſobeied the almighty. Thus we conclude this ſecond part, wherein wee haue noted the diſcretion, and ſtaiednes of <hi>Iacob,</hi> whereby the danger not withſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, he feared not like the faithles <hi>Mam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniſts,</hi> the infirmities of the fathers not <note place="margin">The Mam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monuſts feare.</note> to be excuſed, the preparation of <hi>Iacob</hi> by praier, the loue towardes his family, and how he ſought to ſaue ſome, not hoping to ſaue al: how he tendered the weakeſt, and his authority and gouernment in his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily. The lord powre a great meaſure of his ſpirit into the hearts of our guides to diſpoſe the family of <hi>Iacob</hi> diſcreetly for the preſeruation of Innocent <hi>Ioſeph.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="part">
               <head>The third part.</head>
               <p>The third part is conteining the cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage, deuotion &amp; humility of <hi>Iacob</hi> in his meeting of <hi>Eſau.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>3 <hi>So he went before them &amp; bowed himſelfe to the ground ſeuen times, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til he came neere vnto his brother.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the firſt member of this ſentence where hee ſaieth (ſo hee went before the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) <hi>Moyſes</hi> in this doth declare the cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage of <hi>Iacob,</hi> which like a good captaine
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:177190:27"/>
ledde them the way chearfully. In the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond <note place="margin">Iacob a good Captaine, go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth before hi<hi rend="sup">s</hi> family.</note> member when it is ſaid, <hi>To haue bowed to the ground ſeuen times,</hi> is ſet down his deuotion towards god, &amp; his hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility towards his brother. In euery one of theſe we ſee nothing, but that which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeemeth ſo great a Patriarke, as <hi>Iacob</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Iacob did that which beſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med a Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arke.</note> was. Firſt therefore you heare how he ſet himſelfe foremoſt in the ranck, leaſt by his feare, and towardlines, the reſt ſhould bee diſcomforted. After that the prophet <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Dauid ſlatte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth himſelfe in the fleſh.</note> had put affiance preſumptuouſly in the fleſh, ſlattering himſelfe in his eaſe, that he ſhould not bee moued for euer, he was compelled to confeſſe that when God had hidden his face he was troubled, &amp; to ſing this new ſong: Lord of thy good plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure <note place="margin">Pſal. 30. 28.</note> thou haſt ſtabliſhed ſtrength to thy mountaine. That is to ſay, before &amp; faſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned my Ancre vpon my preſent wealth &amp; peace, or I ſpred forth my ſails at my me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rigales of wind, I preſumed vpon my ſelf. and depended not vpon the free fauor of God: therefore in ſo doing the Lorde by withdrawing his countenance taught me, that my courage was but foole hardines, and in mercy ſhewed me a more ſure hold, where to truſt, euen his mountaine, to
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:177190:28"/>
which his good pleaſure hee hath eſtabli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed ſtrength. Now <hi>Iacob</hi> (we know) ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted <note place="margin">Iacob depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> gods produidence.</note> himſelfe wholy to Gods proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, being ready at all times to reſigne into his hands whatſoeuer God had beſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed vpon him. With this faith therefore <note place="margin">Faith looketh God in the face.</note> which euer looketh God in the face, who performeth that hee promiſeth, hee goeth boldly and couragiouſly before his people. And ſurely if we haue faith, we are not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid, <note place="margin">Mat. 8. 28. Rom. 5. 5.</note> and if we hope we are not aſhamed. For the grimly cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tenance of the tirants vpon earth whom we behold with our bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily eies, are not ſo terrible vnto vs, as the Lord of hoſtes is comfortable, whom our faith, which is our ſpiritual eie, beholdeth, armed for our defence in the heauens. But in this couragiouſnes, <hi>Iacob</hi> hath compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions but a few, for the heads of the people and gouernors of the earth, are content to erceed others in wealth and eaſe, and from <note place="margin">There is no bridle ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> keep vs from coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſſe. Eſau co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming, we ſhrinke backe.</note> the lururious pomp of this worlde, there is no bridle to pluck them back. But whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                  <hi>Eſau</hi> commeth, they are content to looſe their place of dignity, they ſtraine curteſie there, who ſhould go foremoſt. This is true in the gouernors, this is true in the prieſts, they care not who go before them,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:177190:28"/>
when any danger is at hand. But if there bee any time at the length in which they may ceaſe to be apprentiſes to the Diuel, let them not ſtop their eares againſt the great paſtor of the flock, which ſaith, That <note place="margin">Ioh. 10. 11.</note> a good ſhe epheard giueth his life for the ſheep. After the deceaſe of <hi>Moyſes</hi> which couragiouſly went before the people tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough a roring wildernes, his ſeruant <hi>Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſua</hi> was raiſed vp to continew their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ductio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: &amp; becauſe he had many barbarous Giaunts to ſuboue, and perilous exploits <note place="margin">Ioſua. 1. 5. 7. 9.</note> to atchiue, the lord driueth him for wards often with this co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, <hi>Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fortate, &amp;</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Heb. 12. 13.</note> 
                  <hi>roborate valde.</hi> Be ſtrong onely be ſtrong. And that he might make ſtreight ſteps to his feete, leaſt by halting he ſhould turne out of the way, he ſetteth this promiſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him: <hi>Non derelinquam te, ne que deſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ramte,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">The promiſe of God to Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſua.</note> I will not leaue thee, nor forſake thee. And the ſame arme of God, which then ſmote the proud and confounded his enemies before him, which cut <hi>Rechab,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Rechab. 2. Reg. 4. 12.</note> and wounded the dragon, ſhal in our daies alſo wake vp, if we wil be ſtrong in Gods ſtrength, to ſcatter <hi>Eſau,</hi> and his four hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred men before us, as chaffe before the winde. But the ſame exclamation, which
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:177190:29"/>
was woont to be in mens mouthes at the death of the faithful prophets agreeth too wel with our time. Oh the charriots of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and the horſemen of the ſame, for the true prophetes decay, and their praier <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>Reg. 13. 14.</hi>
                  </note> and propheſie was of more force than all our warlike munitions, and whoſe ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual courage was more mighty than the ſturdines of the fleſh. As for the moſt part which remain, they are turned backward, they are like to the ſluggard which ſaith: There is a lion in the ſtreet: yea manie will rather leade the daunce to iniquitie. The courage of <hi>Iacob</hi> was built upon <note place="margin">Iacobs cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage built on faith. Heb. 11. 2. &amp; 12. 1. Iacob a pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terne of chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian courage.</note> faith, therefore is he reckoned in the nom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of thoſe fathers, whoſe ſtedfaſt beliefe the <hi>Apoſtle ſaieth, Hath compaſſed vs with a great number of witneſſes.</hi> Wel we ſee a perfect patterne of chriſtian cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage: the commaundement of God was of more force in him, to make him obey, than the perill that was inſtant to make him afraid.</p>
               <p>There was no other way to <hi>Bethell</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 13. 13.</note> whither he was commanded to returne, but by <hi>Eſau:</hi> ſhould be therefore contemne the voice of God which ſaid, I am the god of <hi>Bethel,</hi> where thou annointeſt the pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:177190:29"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> no: If God have ſaid go to <hi>Bethel,</hi> we may not ſtay in <hi>Padam Aera<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> though <hi>Eſau</hi> with foure hundred men ſtay in the way, (as wee ſhal finde them in the right <note place="margin">We muſt o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey Gods word.</note> way) yet muſt we go to <hi>Bethel.</hi> Obey the word of God, he is the God of <hi>Bethel,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It followeth that <hi>Iacob bowed him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Iacobs deuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militie.</note> 
                  <hi>to the ground ſeuen times vntill he came to his brother.</hi> Here in theſe words (as we haue ſaid before) is compriſed the humility and devotion of <hi>Iacob.</hi> For it is probable, and it is the iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of many, that all this curteſie was not giuen to <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſau</hi> alone, but that hee alſo in the way de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoutly did humble himſelfe before God. This deuotion as it is at all times moſt requiſite, ſo do we then moſt uſe it, &amp; feele the moſt fruit of it, when any danger han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth ouer our heads, and we know by ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience, as many as haue not put awaie the feeling of Gods ſpirite with both their hands, that we are apt by nature to gather pride unto our ſelves in the time of proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perity. And we then forget god moſt, when <note place="margin">In proſperity we gather pride &amp; for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get God.</note> be powreth his benefits moſt beneficially upon us. Therefore both the lord gather by the flitting of his childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by afflictions, to ſet an edge upon their praiers, that
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:177190:30"/>
they may bee keene to cut the cloudes and come before him. Some that are not of <note place="margin">Our earneſt praiers cut the cloudes before God.</note> the ſtubberner ſort he humbleth in ſpirit, and maketh them to goe foorth ſowing in tears, when he ſeemeth to bend the brows of his iudgement upon their terrified con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences. Others that are more unruly, he correcteth with the roddes of men, and ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth <note place="margin">Terrified con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences.</note> them with outwarde puniſhment, teaching them deuotion in the ſchole of af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction. Finally there is no diſpenſation giuen to any of Gods children. For the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle both ſet down appoſſitiue lawe. <hi>As</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">2. Tim. 9. 10.</note> 
                  <hi>manie as will liue godlie in Chriſt Ieſu, muſt ſuffer perſecution.</hi> And when we ſee the fruite of affliction in the perſon of <hi>Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob,</hi> euen deuotion, and a religious care of godlines, whereas to many of us, our eaſe &amp; fulnes of bread hath brought forth contempt and ſecurity, which of us hauing a ſpirit any thing better than the ſpirit of a <hi>Pagan,</hi> wil not wiſh rather to abide all <note place="margin">God corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cteth whom he loueth.</note> his life under the correction of the Lord, the corrector of them whom hee loueth, than by wallowing in ſuch proſperitie, which many are not able to weld, to beco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e like a horſe or mule, which hath no under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtainding? <note place="margin">Pſal. 32. 10</note> The prophet <hi>Dauid</hi> bringeth in
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:177190:30"/>
himſelfe for an example, to confirme this doctrine. <hi>Before I was afflicted,</hi> (ſaith he) <note place="margin">Pſ. 119. 67. 71.</note> 
                  <hi>I went aſtray, but now I keep thy word.</hi> And a little after, <hi>It is good for me that I haue bin afflicted, that I may learne thy ſtatutes.</hi> For this cauſe, ought we all to lift up our weake hands to God, that our true repentance may turne away his an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger. In which hee threatneth to make our ſunne to go down at noon, becauſe he hath <note place="margin">Amos. 8. 9.</note> found us in the number of thoſe, of whom <hi>Moyſes</hi> propheſied thus in his ſong: <hi>He</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Deut. 32. 15.</note> 
                  <hi>that ſhould haue bin vpright, when hee waxed fat, ſpurned with his heele: thou art fatte, thou art groſſe, thou art laden with fatnes, therefore he forſooke the God that made him, and regarded not the ſtrong God of his ſaluation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Queſtionles, if <hi>Moſes</hi> were now aliue, <note place="margin">Deuotion in proſperitie is the ſiſter ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man to the papiſticall daughter of ignorance.</note> to ſtand by, &amp; behold our inſole<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cy, he could not haue met more iumply with our ſin. This is euen the deuotio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that our proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity hath brought foorth. ſiſter german to the papiſtical daughter of ignorance. But how much better were it, if wee would in the dais of our peace, draw our ſleepy ſouls with violence to the tribunal of god? The<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhould not our deuotion betied to affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:177190:31"/>
neither ſhuld our righteouſnes be like the deaw, &amp; the morning cloud. And there we have to learn, that if god ſhould never touch his child re<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he loveth w<hi rend="sup">c</hi> the rod <note place="margin">Without af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction we forget God.</note> of his fatherly diſcipline, but to take the bitte between their teeth, &amp; ſo to run for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards &amp; never to be pluckt back, but as it were, alway to fil the belly like gluttons w<hi rend="sup">c</hi> delicat meats, the ears ful of muſick, to flow in wealth, to excel in authority, to flo riſh in honour, abou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d with friends, richly appareled, garded w<hi rend="sup">c</hi> routs of ſerving me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, <note place="margin">The vanity of the world and worldlings.</note> had in admiratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; revere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce in the face of y world: but what the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> alas, ſhal become of our miſerable &amp; wretched ſouls: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore let us look, what is don in our inward world, let us open I pray you the ſecret &amp; inward eies of our harts, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhal we wel underſtand, that ther is a far other world then this, where far greater riches, &amp; ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher treaſurs are fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, who ſeriouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <note place="margin">We muſt look for the world to come.</note> &amp; hartily trauel to ſeek the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> out. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we muſt not murmor againſt god for his louing correction, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we ſet greater force by the pleaſures of this world, then the obſervatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of his wil &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts.</p>
               <p>Now concerning the humility of <hi>Iacob</hi> to his brother, it is evident in his obeiza<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:177190:31"/>
which he made to him. In that he bowed himſelfe before him, it was the maner of the people that dwelt Eaſtward (among who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                  <hi>Iacob</hi> had bin to be curtous in ſuch <note place="margin">Iacob vſed the curtefie of people that dwelt Eaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward.</note> kind of curtſy, in bowing the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelves down before great perſonages. This exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth us that <hi>Iacob</hi> held the patience of hope: &amp; becauſe he beleeved, therefore he made no haſt but was conte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to be bu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bled to him, ouer who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his father in his prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical bleſſing had ordeined him Lord: not <note place="margin">Gen. 27. 29.</note> becauſe he diſtruſted that which his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther had ſpoken, but partly becauſe he un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood it ſpiritually: &amp; partly becauſe y time was not yet come, in which the king dom of <hi>Iſrael</hi> which was of <hi>Iacob,</hi> ſhould exerciſe that dominio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ouer the <hi>Edomits,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">The Edomies were Eſaus poſterity.</note> which was the poſterity of <hi>Eſau.</hi> And al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the wicked do uſurpe the bleſſing of gon upo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the earth the lawful uſe wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of <note place="margin">Heb. 1. 2.</note> chriſt hath reſtored to none but his bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren: yet the children of god are ſo lifted up w<hi rend="sup">c</hi> the riches of their hope, that w<hi rend="sup">c</hi> an holy conce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pt they vouchſafe not to giue at tenda<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce upo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this world, <hi>where they haue</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Heb. 3. 13.</note> 
                  <hi>no abiding City, but ley for the world, where they look for one to come.</hi> Thus ſhortly haue we performed that we pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed in the beginning.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="54" facs="tcp:177190:32"/>
But before we go farther, we haue one <note place="margin">The promiſes made to the fathers. Gen. 27. 29.</note> thing here to obſerue, concerning the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes made to the fathers. <hi>Iſaac</hi> ſaid, <hi>Be thou lord ouer thy brethren: and let thy mothers children honor thee.</hi> But for al that, <hi>Iacob</hi> ſtowyeth lowe to <hi>Eſaus</hi> foote. Likewiſe to <hi>Salomon,</hi> it is ſaid, <hi>Thy throne O God is for euer and euer.</hi> But <note place="margin">Pſal. 45.</note> he is no ſooner dead, but ten Tribes are rent from his ſonne, &amp; given to a ſtranger: <note place="margin">1 <hi>Reg.</hi> 11. 31.</note> and within 419 yeeres after his poſterity were captiues in <hi>Babylon.</hi> So chriſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed to ratifie the doinges of <hi>Peter,</hi> but <note place="margin">Mat. 16. 19. Gal. 2. 12. 13.</note> yet the ſpirit of God, which ſpake in <hi>Paul,</hi> withſtood him to the face for his diſſimu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation. Notwithſtanding in al theſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes, the word of the lord ſtandeth firme, and his truth re acheth to the heauens. In <note place="margin">The word of God ſtandeth firme. Many of the fathers bare the perſon of Chriſt.</note> the ſcriptures many of the fathers bare the perſon of Chriſt and of the church, and in Chriſt or his church thoſe promiſes the fathers ſawe then no otherwiſe, than <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham</hi> ſaw the daies of chriſt, that is ſpiritually. Concerning <hi>Peters</hi> promiſes, I <note place="margin">Aug. in Pſal. Peters pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes.</note> am of <hi>Auguſtines</hi> iudgement, that many things are ſpoken to <hi>Peter,</hi> which haue not their ful ſenſe, but being applied to the whole Church, for the authority of the
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:177190:32"/>
keies, where of the <hi>Pope</hi> boaffeth, preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding <note place="margin">Ioh. 20. 13. Greg. lib. 4. ſenten.</note> ſucceſſion from <hi>Peter,</hi> As it was gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to <hi>Peter</hi> by name, ſo was it alſo given to the reſt of the Apoſtles generally with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out reſpect of perſons: and ſo to them only which perſiſt in their doctrine. As for the <note place="margin">Heb. 1. 8. Salomon was a figure of Chriſt.</note> eternal throne promiſed to <hi>Salomon,</hi> the Apoſtle to the Hebrewes ſheweth that it both properly belong to Chriſt, of whom he was a figure.</p>
               <p>And as touching <hi>Iacob</hi> whoſe example we haue in hande, the promiſe of his ſove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raignity was fulfilled in <hi>Dauids</hi> daies. <note place="margin">2. <hi>Reg.</hi> 8. 20.</note> from whoſe times the <hi>Edomites</hi> conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued in ſubiection, til the daies of <hi>Ieho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram:</hi> in whoſe time, they rebelled for the ſinnes of the people. The Apoſtle min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Heb.</hi> 7. 9.</note> to prove <hi>Melchizedech,</hi> of whoſe or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der chriſt was a prieſt, to be aboue <hi>Leui,</hi> to whom tythes were due, reaſoneth thus: <note place="margin">The Prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood of Mel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſedech abouc Leui.</note> 
                  <hi>To ſay the truth, Leui alſo which recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued tythes, paid tythes in Abraham, for hee was yet in the loynes of his father, when Melchizech met Abraham.</hi> Euen <note place="margin">The Edo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mites worſhip the ofspring of Iacob.</note> ſo may we reaſon in this promiſe in the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of <hi>Eau,</hi> that ſince the <hi>Edomites</hi> which came out of the Ioines of <hi>Eſau</hi> did worſhip the offſpring of <hi>Iacob:</hi> therefore
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:177190:33"/>
                  <hi>Eſau</hi> did worſhippe <hi>Iacob,</hi> as <hi>Leui</hi> is ſaid to haue worſhipped <hi>Melchizedech.</hi> Nevertheleſſe, to the outwarde appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, <hi>Iacob</hi> is bowed downe before his brother, and diſdained not, for hee looked for the things he ſaw not. And ſurely wold to God, wee had the humility of <hi>Iacob,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Iacobs humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth of hope 1. Pe. 4. 1.</note> which proceedeth of hope: for what though we be wronged of <hi>Eſau!</hi> What though the wicked do aſſault us iniuriouſly? Have we not learned that therein is our confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitie <note place="margin">Math. 11. 29.</note> with Chriſt, who ſaith, <hi>For I am weake and lowly in hart?</hi> What though our bodies be made euen with the ground, ſo that the wicked go ouer vs, and plough long furrowes upon our backes? What is al this to the iniuries of him, which neuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theles triumphed in patience? Onely let <note place="margin">We muſt ſtand to the defence of the trueth. 2. Ti. 2. 24. 2. Ti. 2. 2. The ſeruants of God muſt not ſtriue.</note> vs conſider where about we were: if wee ſtand in the defence of the trueth, there is no ground to bee giuen, but in all this, let vs holde faſt the rule of the Apoſtle: <hi>The ſeruant of God muſt not ſtriue, but muſt be lowely minded.</hi> Behold in this one man, a liuely patterne of long ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, faith, diſcretion, and humilitie. He awaiteth the Lords leaſure patiently, for the accompliſhment of his promiſe. He
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:177190:33"/>
beleeueth that hee ſhall haue dominion, his preſent ſubiection withſtanding: he diſpoſeth his family, and doth homage to his Brother. And hee loſt nothing by it. For it is poſſible, that many of <hi>Eſaus</hi> retinew, did ſeeke more after am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition, and vaine glorie, than after the honeſtie of themſelues, or their Lorde: As diuerſe Sicophantes, <note place="margin">Sycophantes.</note> about great men doe at this daie, vpon reporte that <hi>Iacob</hi> ſhould bee Lord ouer their Lord. The which thing <hi>Eſau</hi> had determined to preuent, by making hauock of him, and all his, had not the Lord vſed the humble ſubmiſſion of <hi>Iacob,</hi> as a meane, not to make them beleeue the Propheſie, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by their outrage was ſtaied. How euer it hee, humilitie was in him a great ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, <note place="margin">By humilitie we draw nees to Chriſt.</note> and moſt excellent: and it is that, wherein wee drawe neere to the image of Chriſt.</p>
               <p>The Lorde therefore of his mercie graunt that wee maie imprint this leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon deepe in our memorie, that the nea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer wee drawe to the Lorde, the more we be diſpleaſed with our ſelues.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="part">
               <pb n="58" facs="tcp:177190:34"/>
               <head>The Fourth part.</head>
               <p>NOw in the fourth part remaineth the bulooked for louing meeting of <hi>Eſau,</hi> and the ioy of them both are deſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed in theſe wordes.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>4 Then Eſau ran to meet him, &amp; fel on his neck, &amp; embraced him, &amp; kiſſed him, and they wept.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>MOyſes hauing declared how <hi>Iacob</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">The ſucceſſe that god gaue to Iacob.</note> bowed himſelfe before his brother <hi>Eſau,</hi> proceedeth to them diligently by cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances, what ſucceſſe God gaue to his deuotion and humilitie, by mentioning the running of <hi>Eſau</hi> to his brother, his embracing him, his falling vpon his neck, his kiſſing him, and his weeping with him. Here we haue found the wiſe man <note place="margin">Pro. 15. 1.</note> as good as his word. <hi>That ſoft and gentle aunſweres and lowly demeanor, brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth anger.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>There is no cauſe why any man ſhould <note place="margin">Eſau his affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</note> cal <hi>Eſaus</hi> affection towardes his brother in queſtion, before that the lord, which can turne the ſtreams backwards, and checke <note place="margin">God turneth al things at his wil.</note> the raging of the ſea, that it ſwel not aboue his pleaſure, had moſtified his heart, and brought him againe for a time to that na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:177190:34"/>
loue of a brother, from which, other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>whiles both before, and after he had verie barbarouſly degenerat. With ſo much the more admiratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, let vs note this great al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teration: <note place="margin">How God turneth the harts of the vngodly.</note> A cruel enuious tirant to become gentle, and louing. But to whom: euen to him whom he purpoſed to murder. Before he came marching againſt him with four hundred men to deſtroy him &amp; his: Now he runneth to him, that hee might preuent him with Brotherly greeting. Before he went to ſtretch foorth his hande to take him by the throte: now ſpredeth his arms abroad to embrace him. Before he would fal vpon him to kil him: &amp; hee now falleth vpon his necke to kiſſe him. At the firſt, he wept for curſt hart (like a woman) when he had loſt his bleſſing, and afterwardes knitting his frowning browes againſt his brother (as the picture of enuy:) But now between ſorrow, for their falling out, and ioy for their pure meeting and reconcile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, he falleth forth into weeping. <note place="margin">The good na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of Eſau was not of himſelfe. The triumph of vertue o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer vice.</note>
               </p>
               <p>And truely heere we haue to note, that this came not of the good nature that was in <hi>Eſau,</hi> but was the onely working of the lord, &amp; the triumph that vertue hath ouer vice: that whereſoever ſhee is moſt hated,
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:177190:35"/>
there doth ſhee ſometimes ſhew her ſelfe. And this is the great puniſhment, that God bringeth on the wicked: Euen as the Poet ſaith, <hi>Virtutem vt videant, intabeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cant<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> relicta.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Virgil.</note> That though they Ioue not vertue, nor cannot like to follow hir: Yet ſhal they pine away with a longing deſire after hir. And this I am ſure ſtriketh deep <note place="margin">Vertue woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience of the wicked.</note> &amp; woundeth the conſcience of the wicked, that though they haue ſet their hartes as hard as an adamant ſtone, and made their faces, like flint to do al kinde of miſchiefe: Yet God by his great mercy and grace, worketh throughout their conſciences, mollifieth their harts to godlines: And ſo doth cauſe them to confeſſe ſometimes that the way of vertue is beſt. As for example. There was neuer ſo unpure and diſſolute an adulterer, but he hath ſaid ſometimes, The chaſt body is beſt. There was neuer ſo great, and cruel a murtherer, but ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times hee calleth to minde that God hath commanded him: <hi>Thou ſhalt do no mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Exo.</hi> 20.</note> There was neuer ſo blaſphemous, nor vile a ſwearer, but ſometimes he hath treambled at gods maieſty. There was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer man ſo proud, &amp; ambitious, but ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times he remembreth that he is but duſt, &amp;
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:177190:35"/>
aſhes. There was neuer ſuch an vſurer, nor couetous wretch, but ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>times he thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth his <hi>Gold &amp; ſiluer ſhal canker, and</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ia.</hi> 5. 2.</note> 
                  <hi>the ruſt of it, ſhall bee a witneſſe againſt him.</hi> There was neuer ſo riotous a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, ſumptuous, &amp; prodigal, but ſometime he condemneth his own doing, and ſaieth with the prophet <hi>Dauid,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſa.</hi> 37. 12.</note> 
                  <hi>The vnrighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous man boroweth &amp; paieth not again.</hi> What ſhould we ſay more: For as it is in a wicked life, euen ſo likewiſe in a corrupt religion. Trueth that is ſtrongeſt, <note place="margin">Trueth in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion forceth the papiſts to confeſſe hir. Merites.</note> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uercommeth all, in religion forceth the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy to confeſſe hir. For their was neuer papiſt, that ſo magniſted merits, and tal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked of his workes of ſupererogations, but ſometimes in his conſcience he wold ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly confeſſe, <hi>That when he had don al,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luk.</hi> 16. 17.</note> 
                  <hi>yet he was vnprofitable.</hi> There was neuer any ſo great an enemie to faith, but when his conſcience was touched with the grief of ſinne, hee would crie aloud, <hi>Faith alone doth iuſtifie.</hi> There was neuer papiſt <note place="margin">Faith a lone iuſtifieth. Fleſhly wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhippings.</note> (I am ſure) yet ſo dronke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that made ſo much of al his fleſhly worſhippings, of organs, &amp; ſinging, of altar, and altar clothes, of fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kencenſe, ſweete ſmelling ſauor, of ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, and ſtreamers, of goodly tunes and
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:177190:36"/>
melodies, of ſiluer croſſes, &amp; chalices, but he hath ſaid ſometime: <hi>Who requireth</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eſai.</hi> 16. 12. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 4. 13.</note> 
                  <hi>theſe things at our hands? The true wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhippers do worſhip in ſpirit and verity.</hi> There was neuer papiſt, in ſo deep a ſleep of pardons, and purgatorie, but hee hath <note place="margin">Pardons, and Purgatorie.</note> ſurely ſaid, <hi>ſuch weak engines can break down, but paper walles: And ſuch colde water, can quench but painted fiers.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>There was neuer <hi>Pope,</hi> nor generall <note place="margin">General counſailes.</note> councel ſo deſperately bent to ſet vp wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipping of Images, but their own harts haue often cried within them: <hi>They haue</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Pſal 115. 5. Images.</note> 
                  <hi>mouthes, and ſpeake not, they haue eies and ſee not, they haue eares and heare not, they haue noſes and ſmell not, they haue hands and handle not, they haue feete and walke not. Thou ſhalt not bow down to them, nor worſhippe them.</hi> There was neuer papiſt ſo blinded <note place="margin">Papiſtical ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtitious Tranſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiation.</note> w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the great abſurdity of tranſubſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tiatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but ſome times ſeing the wine in the Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice, he hath vin afraid to ſay, By this, &amp; by nothing els, let my ſins be waſhed: &amp; ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the cake in the prieſts hands, Thou a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone haſt redeemed me, &amp; alone by thee I look to be ſaued. This much we haue ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken to that inte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, we may ſee the working
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:177190:36"/>
of the lord in the hearts of al his enimies. Refuſe him, how they wil in life, or religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <note place="margin">Papiſts doe ſtriue againſt God and his word.</note> they carry day and night, a witnes in their breſts againſt themſelues, that they rebel &amp; ſtriue not againſt fleſh, &amp; blood, but againſt God, and the trueth of his word.</p>
               <p>Truly ſo may we ſee how god wrought in the hart of <hi>Eſau,</hi> howſoever men talke of the force of nature. We cannot impute it to any thing, but to the miraculus doing of the lord: Who, though we be in the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tome of the ſea, can command the water, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eſai</hi> 45. 15.</note> that it ſhal not drown vs. And, though we <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 2. 18.</note> go through the fire, can keep vs from bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning. To this purpoſe ſpeaketh the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet in the perſon of God: <hi>I will make a couena<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t for them with the wild beaſts,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 2. 18.</note> 
                  <hi>and with the fowles of heauen, and that which creepeth on the earth, and I will break the bow, and the ſworde, and the battel out of the earth.</hi> And if he haue ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> an oth of his domb creatures, that they ſhal not do his choſen harme, much more ſhal he incline the hart of one man to be lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing towards another. Notwithſtanding, <note place="margin">Eſaus gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes was but a violent moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</note> this was but a violent motion of <hi>Eſau,</hi> &amp; therefore endured not. For afterwardes be ſlang away from his brother, and the
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:177190:37"/>
ſpirit of enuy returned vnto him, and poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſed <note place="margin">Gen. 36. Math. 12. 45.</note> him as before. It is nothing there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, that many fond worldlings boſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues (if they haue but one ſparcke of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manity) ſeeing they are caryed about like waterles clouds, and haue no continuance <note place="margin">The wicked continew not in goodnes.</note> in that which is good.</p>
               <p>When <hi>Dauid</hi> both by word &amp; deed, had witneſſed his innocency towards <hi>Saul, At</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">1. Sam. 24. 17. Dauids inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cencie to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards Saul.</note> 
                  <hi>what time he let him eſcape aliue out of the caue of Engeddi,</hi> only cutting off the lap of his coat: the enuious tyrant, which perſecuted him, being conuinced by open <note place="margin">Saul weepeth for his iniury don to Dauid.</note> teſtimonies of his iniurie, lift vp his voice &amp; wept, acknowledging his fault, which ſought after blood without a cauſe. Such is the power of Gods ſpirit, which expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth it ſelfe in the Godly, that the wicked many times are ouercom by their vertues, whom they hate to death. <hi>Eſau</hi> by al like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lihood ſuppoſed (for ſuch is the maner of the wicked to thinke al men like affected <note place="margin">The wicked think al men like to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues.</note> to themſelues) that <hi>Iacob</hi> preſuming vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his fathers bleſſing, would haue behaued himſelfe ſtoutly, and diſdainfully towards him; and therefore he prepared to encoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter with him. But when he drew neer and perceaued his humility, hee was enforced
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:177190:37"/>
with tears to run, and embrace him. And <note place="margin">How we muſt deale with the froward.</note> learn we here, to deale with the frowarde diſcreetly. For, the maintenance of chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian concord, what greater foyſon coulde <hi>Iacob</hi> haue of his humble, &amp; lowly minde: his deſire was only to eſcape aliue, out of the handes of his brother: but the lord did more for him the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he deſired. Behold <hi>Eſau,</hi> in what taking he is, he ru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>neth, he embra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth, &amp; he weepeth. But how now <hi>Eſau:</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">The perplexi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty that Eſau was in.</note> how co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth this to paſſe, that you are ſo kind vpon the ſudden: Is this you, which a little before was ready to burſt with en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uie? I perceaue, it is the lord, that keepeth the keies of al harts, he openeth and <note place="margin">The lord kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth the harts of al men to doe gods pleaſure. Gen. 30. 26.</note> ſhut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth at his pleſure. This roas the bleſſing, that alitle earſt, god gaue to <hi>Iacob,</hi> Thy name ſhalbe caled <hi>Iacob</hi> no more, but <hi>Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el:</hi> becauſe thou haſt had power with god, thou ſhalt alſo preuaile with me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. And now you ſee, he preuaileth with his brother ſo mightily, that a hart of flint is turned into <note place="margin">A field wonne without bloudſhed.</note> a hart of fleſh. The glorie of a field wonne by ſhedding of blood, had not bene compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable to the triumph of this victory, this was indeed to preuaile with men. So tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſaid our ſauiour: <hi>When all thinges are</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Mar. 13. 31.</note> turned topſie turuie: yet the word ſhall
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:177190:38"/>
not fail, but be accompliſhed.</p>
               <p>But to returne a little to the vnſtable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes <note place="margin">God maketh the wicked inſtruments to worke his pleaſure.</note> of <hi>Eſau,</hi> we ſee how the lord can make the wicked, inſtruments to work his plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, maugre their beards, though in their own kind they ſet vp their vriſtles againſt him. <hi>Eſau</hi> ſheweth himſelf wonderful cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous <note place="margin">Eſau curteous to Iacob. Nu. 40. 18 20. Eſaus poſteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty moleſteth Iacobs chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren.</note> to <hi>Iacob,</hi> but his poſterity would giue his children no paſſage in time of their miſerie. Wherein it appeareth, that he had rather ſuborued them to malice, than erhorted them to peace with his bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. The egyptians which lent to the Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raelits (by Gods working) their Jewels, &amp; their <note place="margin">Exo. 12. 35 30. The ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw of the Egyptians.</note> raiment, within a while after, God hardned their harts, were turned againſt them to purſue them, till the Lorde ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>threw them in the midſt of the ſea.</p>
               <p>The ſame people which would haue made chriſt a king, &amp; which ſtrowed their <note place="margin">Ioh. 6 15.</note> garmentes in the way when chriſt paſſed through the ſtreets, and greeted him with <hi>Hoſanna:</hi> the ſelfe ſame people, within a <note place="margin">Mark. 12. 8 9.</note> ſhort time after, were ready to ſtone him to death, and cried, <hi>Crucifie him, Cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Io. 10. 31.</note> 
                  <hi>him,</hi> which had neuer offended them. Thus the inconſtancy of the wicked be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traieth <note place="margin">The vncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancie of the wicked.</note> it ſelfe: they think they haue doone
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:177190:38"/>
God high ſeruice, when they haue left one or two ſhewes of Chriſtianitie, though they return to their vomit. But wee haue not ſo learned chriſt Jeſus: <hi>Eſau</hi> hateth, <hi>Eſau</hi> loueth, and <hi>Eſau</hi> hateth againe. Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertheles, although that the confidence, <note place="margin">The friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly is like the houſe of a ſpider.</note> which is put in the friendſhip of the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly be like the houſe of a Spider, yet herein the louing prouidence of god ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth it ſelfe, when he giueth poore <hi>Iacob</hi> a time of intermiſſion from his tribulati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and perſecutions. And his name is ſo much the more to bee glorified in this, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe where <hi>Iacob</hi> looked for nothing, but thiſtles, he gathered ſigs: &amp; when the dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger was moſt dreadful, the lord as it were <note place="margin">The lord doth work by impoſſibili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties.</note> vpon impoſſibilities, that the knowledge of his power might be grauen more deep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in our breſts, repleniſhed his hart with ioy, and gladnes. And that their condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation may be iuſt, to whom be giucth no grace to beleeue.</p>
               <p>After that the Jewes had beene three<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcore and ten yeares priſoners vnder the <note place="margin">Pſa. 126. 4. Dauids praier for the Iewes.</note> king of <hi>Babel,</hi> the Prophet praieth, <hi>That the lord would bring again their capti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uity, as the riuers in the fourth:</hi> Shewing that he which maketh waters to flow ſo
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:177190:39"/>
abundantly, in baren and dry places of the wildernes, which to vs ſeemeth vnpoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, was alſo able to deliuer his people from the bondage of their enemies. Oh <note place="margin">We muſt fear the lord with a holy feare.</note> that we feared the lord with a holy feare, and that wee were right humble before him like <hi>Iacob.</hi> Then ſhoulde <hi>Eſau</hi> haue no power to hurt vs, though we were as a brand, halfe burned: yet ſhould the Lorde pluck vs out of the fire, and make vs grow <note place="margin">When we thinke god far off, he is moſt nigh to vs.</note> to the bignes of a forreſt. Then, then ſhuld al the creatures of god crie truce with vs, when we do not deny the power of godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, to be of one, and true religion, profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing chriſt rightly and his Goſpel, exten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding <note place="margin">We muſt haue truce with al men.</note> the ſame by our Godly life and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſation, and to become as members of one body, whereof Chriſt is head. And as ſaint <hi>Paul</hi> did write this doctrine to the <note place="margin">We muſt al be members of one body. 1. Cor. 12. 12.</note> Corinthians: Euen ſo he ſpeaketh to vs of England. <hi>As the body (ſaith he) is one, and hath many members, and all the members of that one body, being ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, are one body: euen ſo is Chriſt alſo.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">The church of England as one hath ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny members.</note> This body of Chriſt his Church in Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land is one, and hath many parts, <hi>Engliſh men, Scotiſhmen, Dutchmen, Spaniards, Italia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, Noblemen, Miniſters, Lawyers,
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:177190:39"/>
Marchaunts, Farmors, Artificers, Labo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers,</hi> and <hi>Poorfolke.</hi> And though they bee many, yet are they but one body, which by one ſpirit, are baptiſed into one fayth: Whether they bee <hi>Iewes</hi> or <hi>Grecians,</hi> bond or free, Engliſhmen or any other of the afore named.</p>
               <p>If al were <hi>Nobles,</hi> where were then the <note place="margin">If we were all of one vocati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, there were no common wealth.</note> Preachers: If al were Preachers, where were then the Lawiers? If al were Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yers, where were then the Merchants? If al were Merchants, where were then the farmors, the poor and the laborers? One of theſe cannot ſaie to another, we neede you not, leaſt there ſhould be diuiſion in the body.</p>
               <p>Noble-men, Gentle-men, &amp; Lawiers ſhould not ſay, theſe Miniſters haue too <note place="margin">We muſt not deſpiſe one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother.</note> much, they keepe no hoſpitality, they nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther preach, nor take paines after they haue gotten liuing, they eat of the milke, <note place="margin">Idle miniſters &amp; Preacher's reproued.</note> &amp; cloth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the wool, they become too couetous, not ſeeking to feede the flock of chriſt whom they haue charge of.</p>
               <p>Miniſters &amp; Lawyers, &amp; others ſhould <note place="margin">Vngodlie and vnbrotherlie crueltie.</note> not ſay, many of theſe great men, &amp; gentle men, their partners &amp; ſeruants, doe take away, &amp; withold many mens freeholdes,
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:177190:40"/>
Coppyholdes, and Leaſes, goods, and chattailes at their pleaſure. Take away goods by ſea of Engliſhmen and others, Papiſts and Proteſtantes, ſuch as come next to hand. They maintaine &amp; ſet forth <note place="margin">Backward pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtes in reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion. Such as are of no religion.</note> ſuch as are backwardes in religion, and looke euery day for <hi>Mariana tempora.</hi> They are of <hi>Eſaus</hi> decinue, making no accompt of religion: all is one to them, if they ſerue their preſent turne.</p>
               <p>Noblemen, Miniſters &amp; others ſhould not ſay of the Judges, and Lawiers, that they do nothing but talke, and take mony, defe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d bad cauſes for mony, peruert iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment <note place="margin">Lawes wre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted by crafty Lawiers for lucre-ſake.</note> &amp; iuſtice, for rewards, make Lawes doubtful, that they may expound them as they wil: &amp; picke holes in good Lawes, to make ſtrife, &amp; debate; for increaſe of gaine and lucre. Rich men ſhould not ſaie of <note place="margin">The riche ought not to reuile the poore. The poore ought not to ſpeake all of the rich.</note> poore men, they be idle perſons, Roages, Uagabondes, Darlotes, burne them in the care, hang the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Nor poore men ſhould not ſay of Rich men, theſe Cluttons doe nothing but eat and drink, they haue ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny farmes, many Lordſhippes, many hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, their hawkes, and their houndes, they ſpend more tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> many a good body. They take ſuch great fines, and rents. They
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:177190:40"/>
ſpare themſelues and their friends, and ſo wring the poore ſubiect in ſubſidies, tares, and ſuch like paimentes: that they bee forced to liue miſerably.</p>
               <p>Though faults be faults, and neuer <note place="margin">Faultes to be corrected in ſubiects. Freedome of ſpeach dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous to reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment.</note> ſo true, in reſpect both to be ſpoken of, and corrected in ſubiectes of any degree, by loue and charity: Yet this late freedome of ſpeeches at tables, and ſuch other pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate places tuching the ſtates, may grow dangerous to religion &amp; gouernment.</p>
               <p>And ſurely euen as that famous <note place="margin">Demoſthenes oration to the Athenians.</note> Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor <hi>Demoſthenes</hi> did ſay in an oration to the <hi>Athenians,</hi> When the field is loſt, the Captaines blame the ſouldiers, and the ſouldiers the Captains; the foreward, the rereward: and the Battell, the winges. But if euery one that blameth his fellow <note place="margin">We reproue others when we are moſt blame-wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie our ſelues.</note> had doone his owne dutie, all had beene wel. And ſo if ſuch Noblemen, Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, &amp; others, as blame Miniſters, Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers, &amp; Lawiers: ſuch Merchantes and farmors, as blame Noblemen, Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men &amp; others: and ſuch rich as blame the <note place="margin">Euery man muſt doe his owne dutie. There are many godly and vertuous</note> poore in <hi>England,</hi> would euery one doe his own dutie, al would be ſoone wel. For God be praiſed for it, there be many good Noblemen, and Gentlemen, many lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:177190:41"/>
and godly Preachers, many zealous <note place="margin">of all vocati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, God bee praiſed. The godly being ioyned together in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity, the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked cannot hurt them.</note> and vertuous Lawiers, Merchants, Far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mors, and others; the which if they would throughly agree togither, and helpe one another in their vocations, and callings, all <hi>Eſaus</hi> Canoniſts &amp; Traditionaries, &amp; other had perſons of ech degree, would ſoone either be reformed, or driuen away, allothed and oppreſſed ſhould be at liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty, ſuperſtitious <hi>A Egypt</hi> would bee religious <hi>Iuda,</hi> the ruinous walles of the Church would gliſter with the Law and the Goſpel, <hi>Iacob</hi> and his familie ſhould haue a free and quiet trauell to <hi>Bethel,</hi> the people of God woulde bee brought againe from <hi>Ephraim</hi> to <hi>Beerſaba,</hi> from vice and error, to the vertue and trueth of the Lorde God of our fathers, the <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiles</hi> of Chriſt, and his bleſſed <hi>Martyrs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But alas, the poſtes of Chriſtian con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord <note place="margin">The poſtes of Chriſtian concord de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faced.</note> and amity, be digged vp, the rayles broken, and the pales carried away. So that poore <hi>Iacob,</hi> and his family, are in great daunger. <hi>Eſau</hi> commeth againſt them with 400 men. So that it is not for <note place="margin">Matth. 6. 22.</note> naught, that Chriſt ſaith, <hi>The light of the body is the eie,</hi> then it is not hard to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne by the ſtrangenes of our ſteps, the
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:177190:41"/>
blindnes of eurcies. For if our eies were <note place="margin">Hippocrites ſay they Ioue the lord, and hate their brother.</note> ſingle, I meane if wee were not hippo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crits, we wold not ſay, we loued the lord, &amp; pet hate our brother: Neither would wee fil the mouths of our enemies with laugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, with this woful diſſipation, in which we are diuided againſt our ſelues.</p>
               <p>The death of <hi>Saul</hi> and <hi>Ionathas</hi> was <note place="margin">1. Reg. 31. 5. 2. Reg. 1. 20. Dauid his ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowful ſong for Saul and Ionathas.</note> the ioie of the vncircumciſed <hi>Philiſtines.</hi> Wherefore <hi>Dauid</hi> ſang ſorowfully: <hi>Tel it not in Gath, nor publiſh it in the ſtreets of Aſcalon, leaſt the Daughters of the Philiſtines reioice, leaſt the Daughters of theſe vncircumciſed triumph.</hi> And what ſhal we ſay? Is it not nough that we haue changed the couenant of our God, <note place="margin">The enemies of chriſt laugh his goſpel to ſcorne. 1. Cor 3. 3. Saint Paul re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buketh the Corinthians for diſſenu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. Mark. 3. 24.</note> vuleſſe wee make the enemies of Chriſts croſſe to laugh his goſpel to skorn? Saint <hi>Paul</hi> when he hard of contentions among the Corinthians, asked them earneſtlie thereupon: Are yee not carnal? and it is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hemently to be feared, ſeing that eur con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouerſies haue paſſed the bands of chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, leaſt we alſo be carnal. And it muſt bee true that Chriſt ſaieth, <hi>Omne regnum in ſe diuiſum deſolabitur.</hi> Euery gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment diuided within it ſelfe ſhalbe ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thrown. <hi>Iacob</hi> and <hi>Eſau</hi> run together and
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:177190:42"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="73" facs="tcp:177190:42"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="74" facs="tcp:177190:43"/>
meet one another, louingly. But we with al the rancor of our vnquiet hearts which boile ouer to the offence of many, run a ſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der: one ſort giueth no place to the trueth, another <note place="margin">Our abuſes declared.</note> raiſeth ſlanders to ſtrengthen the wreſtes of diſcord to our ſhames (we may ſpeak it) the peace of the church is broken. <hi>Iacob</hi> &amp; <hi>Eſau</hi> embrace one another, but we diſgrace one another, reioiſing in their <note place="margin">How we back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bite one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</note> tranſgreſſion, ouer whom we haue power to inſult. <hi>Iacob</hi> &amp; <hi>Eſau</hi> kiſſe one an other, but we kick one another. They weepe one vpon anothers neck, but one of vs ſcorn a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother behind his back. And now I pray you tel me: Is this the fruit of chriſtiani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty? Is this the meed of 28. yeers labor, to make the ſun a witnes againſt vs, by ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring <note place="margin">The Sunne a witnes againſt our wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes. Eph. 4. 26. Gal. 5. 15. Enme cauſeth vs to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed one of another. Mat. 6. 12. How we do a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſe the lords praier.</note> it to goe down vpon our wrath?</p>
               <p>Let vs take heede (being warned of the holy ghoſt) leſt while we bite one another, we be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſumed one of another. If we ſeek not to haue peace with all men (as much as in vs lieth) our daily praier is that gods ve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gea<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce may light vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs: ſeeing that for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giuenes of ſins we craue of the lord, is ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the proportio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the forgiuenes, which we extend to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> haue offended vs.</p>
               <p>If therefore wee haue any bowels of
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:177190:43"/>
compaſſion in vs, if there bee any ſpark of charity raked vp in the ymbers of any <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Phi.</hi> 2. 1.</note> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion towards God, any loialty towards his church, or any chriſtian ſobriety, tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perance or lowlines in our ſelues, let vs now crie truce, let vs meet togither in cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, let vs embrace togither in godly <note place="margin">We muſt now cry truce and be in loue and charitie with al men.</note> vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, let vs meete together in true peniten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy: Let vs all (as one man) returne to the lord, that he may turne to vs, &amp; remember our wickednes no longer.</p>
               <p>The lord in the treaſures of his rich <note place="margin">We muſt pray for al magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates.</note> mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy make the day ſtar to ſhine bright in the barts of the magiſtrats, &amp; ſhape the harts of the people to al godly obedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, that <hi>Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cobs</hi> wrongs may be righted, &amp; the tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of <hi>Eſau</hi> may bee ſuppreſſed: that the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily of <hi>Iacob</hi> may be diſcreetly diſpoſed, <note place="margin">We muſt pray for the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord &amp; vnity of the church.</note> that his chriſtian courage may not be aba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, that his deuotion &amp; humility may be ſound &amp; perfect, that his godly attoneme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t may be accompliſhed. So that a chriſtian concord being wrought in al ſincerity and ſimplicity, of Gods eternal teſTament, we al (as many as purpoſe to lift vp pure ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds without wrath or douting) may one with another run with patience to the eternall throne of grace, through Jeſus Chriſt our Lord, Amen.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="prayer">
            <pb facs="tcp:177190:44"/>
            <head>A PRAYER AGAINST the enimies of the Church of Chriſt, vnder the borowed <hi>name or ſpeach of</hi> IACOB.</head>
            <p>O Eternal God and moſt mightie ſhephcard of Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raell, which commandeſt Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob thy <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ge.</hi> 31. 3.</note> ſeruant to return out of Meſopotamia to Bethel the land of his fathers, and to his kindred, promiſing to be with him, and that hee ſhould pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ge.</hi> 32. 8.</note> with men: the which thy commaundement he obeing, diddeſt according to that thy promiſe cauſe him to preuaile with Eſau his Brother, who came againſt him with foure hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ndred men, thinking to haue ouerrunne him &amp; his family.
<pb facs="tcp:177190:44"/>
But thou hauing the keies of all hearts to open, and ſhut at thy pleaſure, doeſt miracu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſly, and as it were by im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſsibilities make the ſtonie hart of the moſt cruell, to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come a heart of fleſh, and the wicked to do thy wil: we ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thy ſeruants, O thou god of Bethel, do lift vp our eies to the throne of thy maieſty with an holy feare &amp; faithful harts, moſt humbly beſeeching thee to look down with thy merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful eies vpon Iacob (we mean thy Church) that that excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municat &amp; Antichriſtian <note place="margin">Reuc. 9. 10. 11.</note> Eſau (we mean the pope) that foule dragon Abaddon with his lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſtes,
<pb facs="tcp:177190:45"/>
Traditionaries, Symo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtes, and domb dogs, and al idle hierlings which are care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les of thy family, may be roo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted out of thy vineyeard, who go about and practiſe by all poſsible means to deface and hinder the proceedings of Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob &amp; of thy faithfull ſeruant, our gratious Quene Eliza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth, whom thou haſt ſette to gouern and raigne ouer vs, to ſet forth &amp; maintain the prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching of the goſpel of thy ſon Chriſt Ieſus, &amp; to place in the roumes of Godlie Paſtours, dumb dogs, Traditionaries, <note place="margin">Eſai. 56. 20.</note> and idle hirelings, which ſhall ſeek to fil their bellies, &amp; not
<pb facs="tcp:177190:45"/>
caring to feede the beloued flock of thy ſon Chriſt, whom he hath ſo deerely redeemed, with his own precious blood: &amp; alſo to break in ſunder the vnity, and concord of thy ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick church, and this com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon wealth, which the godlie learned compare to a defece, about which there be poſtes, pales, and railes, that ſo long as they be faſtened the one to the other, ſo long they keep in &amp; out all things accordingsly: but if any of them be pulled a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way or broken down, the reſt are more eaſier to bee ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thrown: So that the wild boar <note place="margin">Pſal. 70. 13.</note> of the wood, and beaſts of the
<pb facs="tcp:177190:46"/>
fielde maie haue their waie to root it vp, and eat the grapes of the vineyeard. Power out therefore, O omnipotet god, vpon thine elect, that as mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of one bodie, whereof chriſt is the head, we may pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe <note place="margin">1. Cor. 3.</note> one true faith and religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on agreeable to thy moſt ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly words, hauing pityiful harts towards poorlacob, yea &amp; to our own ſoules, we maie alſo with Iacobs humilitie, ſimpli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city, and vprightnes of ſpirits rack our powers to the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt pin for the aduancement of the glory of god. To whom bee all honor and praiſe both now and euer.</p>
            <closer>Amen.</closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:177190:46"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
